<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The touch-stone of the reformed gospel wherein the principal heads and tenents of the Protestant doctrine (objected against Catholicks) are briefly refuted. By the express texts of the Protestants own Bible, set forth and approved by the Church of England. With the ancient fathers judgements thereon, in confirmation of the Catholick doctrine.</title>
            <author>Heigham, John, fl. 1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1370E</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216621</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828346</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828346</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32773</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32773)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1866:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The touch-stone of the reformed gospel wherein the principal heads and tenents of the Protestant doctrine (objected against Catholicks) are briefly refuted. By the express texts of the Protestants own Bible, set forth and approved by the Church of England. With the ancient fathers judgements thereon, in confirmation of the Catholick doctrine.</title>
                  <author>Heigham, John, fl. 1639.</author>
                  <author>Kellison, Matthew, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The last edition exactly corrected.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[10], 141, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Heigham.</note>
                  <note>Includes index at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Lambeth Palace Library, London.</note>
                  <note>Formerly attributed to Matthew Kellison, Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32773:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32773:1"/>
            <p>THE TOUCH-STONE OF THE Reformed Goſpel: Wherein The principal Heads and Tenents of the Proteſtant Doctrine (obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt Catholicks) are briefly refuted, <hi>By the expreſs Texts of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants own Bible, ſet forth and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>With the ancient Fathers judgements thereon, in confirmation of the Catholick Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The laſt Edition exactly Corrected.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke. 19.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
Out of thy own mouth will I judge thee.</q>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:32773:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32773:2"/>
            <head>To the Catholick READER Health, and incouragement in his Holy Faith.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEfore thou peruſe this little Book, I would intreat thee to read theſe enſuing Points which are very neceſſary for thy better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1. The firſt is,</hi> that in the Text of Scripture alledged throughout this Treatiſe, it is not ſpecified out of which <hi>Engliſh Bible</hi> the ſaid paſſages are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, for as much, as this were over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roubleſome unto thee, ſince <hi>England</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath ſet forth within theſe few years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ast, a great number of ſeveral ſorts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Bibles, far different one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her; So that our Adverſaries (to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hom I wiſh from my heart, as I do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thee, that this little Book may
<pb facs="tcp:32773:3"/>prove profitable) have not all one ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Bibles themſelves. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing know for certain, that they are a faithfully taken out of the Bibles <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarto; and Octavo,</hi> printed at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by <hi>Robert Barker,</hi> anno <hi>1615.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as if by chance any one ſhall ſhew the ſome other Bible, wherein they are n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſet down, word for word, as here the are; yet reſt aſſured, that thou ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> find them ſo written, and faithful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cited out of the foreſaid Edition <hi>Robert Barker,</hi> ſet forth by his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ſpecial commandement.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. The ſecond is,</hi> That thou a mire the ſplendor of Truth, which ſuch, and ſo refulgent, that notwit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding our Adverſaries main a ſerious endeavours to obſcure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſame, by ſo many varieties of Tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations, and by ſuch a number of gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> corruptions and falſifications; yet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> condemnation is ſo expreſly ſet do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in this their own <hi>Bible,</hi> and is ſo cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to all the world, that nothing elſe needfull hereto, but that thou know read, and have thine eyes to behold
<pb facs="tcp:32773:3"/>ſame, at the opening of this their Book, This cannot chuſe but be an exceeding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omfort to Catholicks, concerning the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>prightneſs of their cauſe, to offer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hemſelves to be tryed, and to confound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir adverſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ries by their own Bible: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he tranſlation whereof notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th in a number of places, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>articularly in many of thoſe that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n queſtion, ſwerve and differ noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly from the authentical Latin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to the incredible diſparagement, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd obſcuring of the Catholick cauſe. Never did yet (nor I preſume dare) our Adverſaries offer to give the like ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>antage unto us, as to ſtand to be tried <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y our Tranſlations, and that in above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fty Heads, and Points of Doctrine. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat are this day in controverſy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ween us.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3. The third is,</hi> That when thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alt urge, or alledge any paſſage, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avour of thine own faith and doctrine; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f any one return their charge, be it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her by way of recrimination &amp; blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of the Roman Church, or by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dging ſome obſcure texts, and thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:32773:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:32773:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:32773:5"/>ill underſtood, to counterpoyze ſuch as are brought by thee; do thou ſhew them amiably, that this is not to proceed in due order, nor to deal with thee as they ought, in oppoſing a paſſage dark, and obſcure, to confound another that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt clear and evident. For example when we ſet before their eyes theſe few words (as clear as the Sun at noone day) <hi>Take, eat, this is my body, this is my bloud which ſhall be ſhed for you,</hi> &amp;c. (Mark <hi>14.25.</hi>) they will ſtraight ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to have found another importan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> place, yea, and to have given us th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> overthrow, if they preſently reply, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Saviour ſaith in S. John <hi>6.63 The fleſh profiteth nothing, the word that I ſpeak unto you, they are ſpirit and they are life;</hi> a paſſage far mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obſcure than that which is in queſtion and which affirmes nothing leſs, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that which they pretend to prove there by. For how abſur'd were it to ſay, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the fleſh of Chriſt profiteth nothing And if (as they themſelves ſay) w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> muſt interpret one paſſage by another thou doubtleſſe it is better to explicat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:32773:5"/>an obſcure one, by one that is clear, than one that is clear, by a paſſage obſcure; and that one Text give place to many, rather than many to one.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4. The fourth is,</hi> That if they ſhall reject any of the paſſages which thou produceſt, pretending the ſame to be <hi>Apocryphal;</hi> know, that to prevent this objection, no ſuch Scriptures, as they call <hi>Apocryphal</hi> are here produced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but that alwayes there go accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with them, others that are <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical,</hi> even by their own confeſſion: And ſo far as <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Scriptures ſhall, and do agree with <hi>Canonical,</hi> they themſelves by their own Rule, are bound to receive them. Which will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſtop their mouth in their common pretence of Conference of places; for rarely haſt thou here leſs then three, or four ſeveral paſſages cited at large (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides references) for the proof of every ſeveral Point: All our Adverſaries put together, being never able in their defence to do the like; that is, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſo many in number, ſo expreſſe and clear, and for ſo great a number
<pb facs="tcp:32773:6"/>of Controverſies, as are here diſputed and couched in ſo little a Treatiſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The fifth is,</hi> that if they ſhall contend with thee, not about the words themſelves, as being clear, but about the ſenſe and meaning of them; for ſuch places, I ſay, as may be ſubject to this cavil, thou ſhalt forthwith have recourſe unto that which the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures call, <hi>the Rule of faith,</hi> that is, to the ever-conſtant and uniform Judgment of the Church, and Ancient Fathers, who, in every Age ſince Chriſt, have underſtood the point in queſtion, in that ſenſe which Catholicks do. An example whereof thou maiſt lay down before them out of that learned Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, intituled. <hi>A Manuel of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi> debating the queſtion of the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament.</hi> Which having done, bid them do the like, and thou wilt yield unto them; (a thing which they can never peform.) So as no man of reaſon will reject this <hi>Rule,</hi> grounded ſo clearly in holy Scripture, and prefer the private interpretation of ſome ſilly Cobler before <hi>S. Chryſoſtom,</hi> of a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker
<pb facs="tcp:32773:6"/>before <hi>S. Baſil,</hi> of ſome Tinker be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Tertullian,</hi> or of any Noveliſt whatſoever, before the judgement of the the Church, and the whole ſtream of the Holy Fathers.</p>
            <p>This point therefore being ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, ſhall be the firſt, which I will fortifie, and prove by the word of God in this preſent Treatiſe, I mean this <hi>Rule;</hi> and therefore in no wiſe forget, alwayes to involve thine Adverſary within this <hi>Rule,</hi> as often as he ſhall prove ſo unruly, and thou ſhalt be ſure to get the victory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſixth and laſt point is,</hi> That I here proteſt, in the preſence of God (whom I call to witneſs in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, and pray thee alſo to call upon, for the ſalvation and reduction of all thoſe that walk aſtray) that it is not in the power of any one, no not of all our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries that are in <hi>England,</hi> to find in their own <hi>Bible,</hi> one onely expreſſe Text, I ſay, <hi>one onely, in their own Bible,</hi> by which they can poſſibly prove, <hi>one onely</hi> point of their falſe Doctrine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> without their uſual art of adding, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing,
<pb facs="tcp:32773:7"/>chopping or changing it by ſome interpretation, or other: which yet ſhould be to alter the Text it ſelf, and to employ mans fancy, inſtead of the pure word; a thing by their own confeſſion, flatly forbidden them, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting, that the <hi>Word of God,</hi> doth in ſuch ſort contain all that which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation, that it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful neither for men, nor Angels, to add, diminiſh, or alter any part thereof; and commanding their followers and adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, utterly to renounce all Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Cuſtom, Multitude, humane wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Judgment, Decrees, Edicts, Counſels, Viſions, yea, and Miracles themſelves, to the contrary.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32773:7"/>
            <head>THE TOUCH-STONE Of the REFORMED GOSPEL.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Proteſtants affirm. I.</hi> That there is not in the Church <hi>one,</hi> and that an infallible <hi>Rule,</hi> for under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Holy Scriptures, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in matters of Faith.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Having then gifts, differing according to the grace that is given to us, whether Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> (that is interpretation) <hi>according to the proportion</hi> (or Rule) <hi>of faith,</hi> Whence we gather, that Prophecy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Rule</hi> of faith, is one of the gifts which God beſtoweth on his Church. Therefore there is in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32773:8"/>Church <hi>one,</hi> and that an infallible <hi>Rule,</hi> to underſtand the holy Scriptures by.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> 3.16. <hi>Nevertheleſs, whereto we have already attained. Let us walk by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame thing.</hi> Lo how plainly the Apoſtle ſpeaks in this ſecond place, of a certain <hi>Rule</hi> to walk by: clearly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſing, that in matters of faith, we can never be of the ſame minde, unleſſe we walk by the ſame <hi>Rule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. <hi>And as many as walk according to this</hi> Rule, <hi>peace be on them, and mercy.</hi> And 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.15. <hi>Having hope when your faith is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, that we ſhall be enlarged by you, according to our</hi> Rule, <hi>abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to preach the Goſple in the Regions beyond you, and not to boaſt in another mans line.</hi> Here again, becauſe every man is to direct, and order his belief, according to the doctrine of the Church, therefore it is called by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> both the <hi>Rule,</hi> &amp; <hi>Line</hi> of our holy faith.</p>
               <p>Again 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. <hi>But if any man ſeem to be contentious, we have no ſuch Cuſtome, nor the Churches of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32773:8"/>God.</hi> Lo how S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtill pleads the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the contentious: which if it could, then by the ſole preſcription of twenty or thirty years, and by the authority of ſo few Paſtors, ſtop the mouthes of new Sect-maſters, what ought not the Cuſtome of ſixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, and the decrees of ſo many hundred Paſtors gain of reaſonable, modeſt and humble men?</p>
               <p>And here I would have it to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that this Analogy, or <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> (beſides the titles already recited) the holy Scripture in other places, calls by the name of <hi>Form of Doctrine,</hi> Rom. 6.17. <hi>A thing made</hi> ready to our hand, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. The <hi>Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum</hi> (or Treaſure) <hi>committed to the Churches truſt,</hi> and ever moſt careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be kept by her. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.20. And withall in the very ſelf ſame pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, always ſtileth that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this <hi>Rule,</hi> by the name of <hi>Diſunion, Diſcord, Diſobedience, forſaking of our firſt Vocation, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, Contention, Prophane and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32773:9"/>vain babling, Oppoſition of ſciences,</hi> &amp;c. Whence plainly appear how great the neceſſity is for every Chriſtian to keep this <hi>Rule;</hi> the leaſt breach whereof, doth preſently crack his Chriſtian cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with the Church of God, and with all good Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Acts</hi> 15 2. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.16.</p>
               <p>¶ According to this very <hi>Rule,</hi> the Ancient Fathers affirm the ſame. S. <hi>Irenaus l.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 45. <hi>Tert. de praeſor.</hi> And <hi>Vincent. Lyr. in ſuo Commonito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio,</hi> ſaith: <hi>It is very needfull in regard of ſo many errors proceeding from the miſ-interpretation of Scriptures, that the Line of Propheticall and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical expoſition ſhould be directed according to the</hi> Rule <hi>of the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical and Catholick ſenſe.</hi> Thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth this moſt worthy witneſſe. <hi>Tertul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Praeſcrip. Adv. Haereſ. Cap.</hi> 15, <hi>&amp; Cap.</hi> 19. Saith. <hi>We do not admit our Adverſaries to diſpute out of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, till they can ſhew who their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors were, and from whom they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32773:9"/>the Scriptures. For the orderly courſe of doctrine requires, that the firſt Queſtion be, whoſe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are by right, from whom, and by whom, and to whom the</hi> Form <hi>of Chriſtian Religion was delivered? O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe preſcribing againſt him as a ſtranger &amp;c.</hi> Thus he.</p>
               <p>Behold, how theſe two laſt ancient Fathers, lay hold of, and urge theſe two very terms, <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>Form</hi> of Faith; and Religion even as before the Holy Scripture did, from whence doubtleſſe they took the phraſe. And with very great reaſon, for the knowledge of <hi>Tradition</hi> (which is the <hi>Form or Rule</hi>) goes before the knowledge of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture for the <hi>Rule</hi> muſt be firſt known, before the thing <hi>ruled</hi> can be aſſuredly known; as the Carpenter cannot know certainly, that he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eaſured his timber, nor the Taylor, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he hath meaſured his cloth aright, except he firſt aſſuredly know, that is meaſure be both true and right: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Rule of Faith,</hi> to wit, the Summe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f thoſe points that every Chriſtian is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32773:10"/>bound expreſly to know, as delivered to him from hand to hand, is the knowledge of <hi>Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Proteſtants affirm. II.</hi> That in matters of <hi>Faith</hi> we muſt not rely upon the Judgement of the Church and of her Paſtors, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the <hi>written Word.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their own Bible, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.2. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Scribes and the Phariſees ſit in Moſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeat, all therefore whatſoever they bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you obſerve, that obſerve and do.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which words, <hi>Chriſt</hi> not only com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mands us in matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> to have recourſe to ſomewhat elſe beſides th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> onely <hi>written words</hi> (to wit, to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the Church), but bids more over, to obey them: and that not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in ſome principal matters, but in al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whatſoever, without diſtinction o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> limitation. Therefore in matters o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> faith, we are not tied to rely onel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon the written word.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:32773:10"/>
                  <hi>Luke,</hi> 10.16. <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me; and he that deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth you, deſpiſeth me: and he that diſpiſeth me, diſpiſeth him that ſent me.</hi> Here again <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth and giveth as much authority to the Preachers of the <hi>Word,</hi> as he can poſſibly do to the word it ſelf, ſaying: <hi>He that heareth you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matth,</hi> 16.19. <hi>Whatſoever thou ſhalt binde on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven: and whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe in earth, ſhall be looſed in heaven.</hi> Where it is to be noted, that he doth not ſay <hi>whoſoever</hi> but <hi>whatſoever;</hi> giving us thereby to underſtand, that not onely the bonds of ſins, but as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell all other knots and difficulties in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atters of faith, are to be looſed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Peter,</hi> and by the Paſtors that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed him in the Church.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8. <hi>Aggeus</hi> 2.1. 2. <hi>Cron.</hi> 19.8. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the end.</hi> 2. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heſ.</hi> 2.15.</p>
               <p>¶ The holy Fathers that affirm the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me, are S. <hi>Gregory NaZ In orat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. Tertul. lib. de praeſcrip. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32773:11"/>har. S, Cyprian lib.</hi> 1. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 3. <hi>S. Aug. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cont. Croſc. cap.</hi> 33. <hi>and lib. cont. Fund. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Vincent. Lyr. in ſuo commonit.</hi> And S. <hi>Anſelm lib. de incar. cap.</hi> 1. writing to Pope Urban. ſaith thus unto him: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> other is more rightly referred to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, whatſoever ariſeth in the Church againſt the Catholick faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>They affirm. III.</hi> That the Scriptures <hi>are eaſie to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,</hi> and that therefore non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ought to be reſtrained from readin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of them.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their own Bible, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Where S. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſpeaking of S. <hi>Pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Epiſtles, ſaith: <hi>In which are ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> things hard to be underſtood, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> they that are unlearned, and unſtabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> wreſt, as they do alſo the other Scri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, unto their own deſtruction.</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all unlearned Reformers, both rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32773:11"/>and are allowed to read thoſe hard things (yea, the Book of <hi>Apocalyps</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo yet harder) without any reſtraint to man, or woman, which yet they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not: therefore they wreſt them, as alſo other Scriptures, to their own deſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 8.30. <hi>And Philip ſaid, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeſt thou what thou readeſt? And he ſaid: How can I, except ſome man ſhould guide me?</hi> Where firſt may be noted, that this Noble Eunuch freely confeſſed, he could not underſtand the Scriptures without an interpreter to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound them, albeit he was a great, and ſerious ſtudent in them, and withal a holy and humble man, as <hi>S. Hierom</hi> noteth of him, <hi>Epiſt. ad Paulin. de ſtud. Script.</hi> And next that he ſaith, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſome man guide me:</hi> So as he fled not to his private ſpirit, nor yet to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of place with place, as our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries do. Therefore the Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re not eaſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.25. and 27. <hi>Chriſt</hi> called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wo of his Diſciples fools, and ſlow of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eart, <hi>&amp;c. And beginning at Moſes,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32773:12"/>and all the Prophets, he expounded unto them in all the Scriptures, the things concerning himſelf.</hi> How then are the Scriptures ſo eaſily to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the unlearned, when <hi>Chriſts</hi> Diſciples themſelves could not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, till firſt they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.1. <hi>&amp;c,</hi> The Angel ſpeaking of <hi>the Book ſealed with ſeven ſeals, wept much, becauſe no man in heaven nor in earth, was able to open the Book, neither to look thereon.</hi> A ſtrange caſe! to read in Scripture it ſelf, that the book of Scripture ſhould be ſhut with ſo many ſeals: but much more ſtrange, that even in <hi>S. John</hi> and the Apoſtles time, none could be found, neither in heaven, nor earth, able to open the ſame, nor to look thereon, which every Apprentice now adayes, without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> difficulty will undertake to do.</p>
               <p>See more 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11 <hi>and</hi> 36. <hi>Luke</hi> 24..45. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10 <hi>Luke</hi> 8.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 54. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.50. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 7. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.6. <hi>John</hi> 5.35. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 18. <hi>and</hi> 34. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:32773:12"/>¶ The holy Fathers that affirm the ſame are, S. <hi>Iraenus l.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 27. <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen l. cont. Celſ. S. Amb. Epiſt.</hi> 44. <hi>ad Conſtant.</hi> Where he calleth it: <hi>A ſea, and depth of prophetical riddles,</hi> S. Jer. <hi>in praefat. comment. in</hi> Epheſ. 5. And S. Aug. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 119. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. ſaith: <hi>The things of Scripture that I knew not, are many more then thoſe that I know,</hi> So S. Greg. <hi>hom.</hi> 6. <hi>in</hi> Ezech. and many other Fathers confeſs the ſame of themſelves. S. <hi>Denis</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corinth,</hi> cited by <hi>Euſcbius lib.</hi> 7. <hi>hiſt. Eccl.</hi> 20. ſaith: <hi>Of this Book</hi> (of Scripture) <hi>this is my opinion, that the matter thereof is far more profound then my wit can reach unto.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>They affirm. IV.</hi> That Apoſtolical <hi>Traditions,</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Cuſtoms of the Church, (not found in the <hi>written word</hi>) are not to be received, nor to oblige us.</head>
               <p>Contrary to the expreſs word of their own Bible 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Therefore Brethren ſtand faſt, and hold the</hi> Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32773:13"/>
                  <hi>which ye have been taught, whether by word or by Epiſtle.</hi> Hence it is clear, that ſome Traditions were delivered to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> by word of mouth, and thoſe of equal authority with what was written, if not of more: for the holy Ghoſt doth name them firſt, as they were indeed the firſt in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,) yea it is certain, that before the new Teſtament was written, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles delivered all by Tradition, and word of mouth. Therefore Apoſtolical Traditions are to be received, and do oblige us.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Theſ. 3.6. <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w I command you brethen, in the name of our Lord</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>that ye with draw your ſelves from every brother that walketh dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly, and not after the</hi> Tradition <hi>which he received of us.</hi> He ſaith not, <hi>I councel you,</hi> but I <hi>command you.</hi> But theſe men, rejecting all Traditions, walk diſordered: therefore they break the Apoſtles commandment. Yea, they <hi>ſtand</hi> not, but are fallen; they let go, what the word it ſelf doth will them to <hi>hold:</hi> and therefore in the name of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32773:13"/>our Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> let all good men withdraw from them.</p>
               <p>1. Cor. 11.2. <hi>Now I praiſe you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hren, that you remember me in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hings, and keep the</hi> Traditions, <hi>as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ave delivered them unto you.</hi> But theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eject all Traditions: therefore needs muſt S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak thus unto them: Now (none of my brethren) I diſpraiſe you, for that you forget me in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hings, and keep not the Traditions, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have delivered them unto you.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if nothing at all be to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieved, but onely that which is left us written, wherein ſhould the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave exerciſed herſelf from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> the ſpace of two thouſand ſix <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undred years?</p>
               <p>See more 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <hi>John</hi> 20.30 <hi>and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.25. <hi>and</hi> 16.12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16.34. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>ep. John.</hi> 12.3 <hi>ep. of S. John</hi> 13. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.4. <hi>and</hi> 15.28.</p>
               <p>¶ The Fathers that affirm the ſame, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re <hi>S. Iraeneus l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Origen. in cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ad Rom. S. Damaſ. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>S. Chryſoſt. in</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. And <hi>S. Baſil.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32773:14"/>de Spiritu ſancto</hi> ſaith: <hi>ſome things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> have from Scripture. (other things fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the Apoſtles, both which have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> force unto Godlineſs.</hi> S. Chryſoſtom 4. in 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> faith <hi>It is a Traditi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſeek thou no further.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>They affirm. V.</hi> That a man, by his own underſtandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or private ſpirit, may rightly jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and interpret Scripture.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words their own Bible 1. <hi>Cor</hi> 12.8. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 10. <hi>To one is given by the ſpirit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> word of wiſedome: to another the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> of knowledge by the ſame ſpirit: to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother the working of miracles: to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Propheſie, to another diſcerni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of ſpirits: to another kinds of tongue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to another the interpretation of tongu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> but all theſe worketh that one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the ſelf ſame ſpirit, dividing to ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> man ſeverally, as he will.</hi> Where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Apoſtle in expreſs words, oppoſeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> refelleth this unſavory doctrine, tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32773:14"/>that the gift of propheſying, or truly to interpret the holy Scripture, is not given to all the faithfull, but to ſome only in particular: yea, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth that one may have the gift, even to work miracles, and yet may want the gift truly to interpret the Word of God. Therefore a man by his own private ſpirit cannot rightly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret Scripture.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.20. <hi>Knowing this first, that no Propheſie of the Scripture is of any private interpretation, for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie came not in old time</hi> (in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, <hi>or at any time</hi>) <hi>by the will of man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut holy men of God spake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> See how clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the Apoſtle taketh this faculty and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uthority from a private and prophane man, reſtraining the ſame to a company <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſociety of men, and thoſe alſo of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome ſpecial note for their ſanctity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd holineſſe, aſſuring us, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pake, as they were moved by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>1 John 4.1. <hi>Beloved, beleeve not very ſpirit, but try the spirits, whether
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32773:15"/>they are God.</hi> By which words we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> taught, that the ſpirits of others are t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be examined, whether they proce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> from God or not: but this Caveat ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be underſtood of the ſpirit of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> whole Church, ſince then it would fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that there ſhould be none left t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> try the ſaid ſpirit of the Church (eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> particular man being included therei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>). If then it be to be meant of priva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> men (as needs it muſt) it follows, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a private ſpirit cannot be this Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſince it ſelf is to undergo the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and examination of ſome other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>¶ The Fathers, that affirm the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are <hi>S. Aug. epiſt.</hi> 16.2. <hi>and l. de B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſmo cap.</hi> 18. <hi>ad Epictetum. S. Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> epiſt.</hi> 78. <hi>S. Amb epiſt.</hi> 32. <hi>S. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> epiſt.</hi> 53. <hi>S. Hier. lib. cont. Lucifer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nos. Vincent. Lyr. cont. prophan. her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> novitates.</hi> Yea, <hi>Martin Luther</hi> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (the Proteſtants great Grand-F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) ſaith <hi>lib. de poteſtate Papae: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> are not certain of any private perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> whether he hath the revelation of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no: but that the Church hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> we ought not to doubt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:32773:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>They affirm. VI.</hi> That S Peters faith hath failed.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible <hi>Luke</hi> 22.31.32. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imon, behold Sathan hath deſired to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ave you, that he may ſift you as wheat: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut I have prayed for thee, that thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aith fail not.</hi> Sathan required to ſift <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem all (the Apoſtles) but our Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere prayed for <hi>Peter</hi> onely, that his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith principally might not fail. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore S. <hi>Peters</hi> faith hath not failed.</p>
               <p>Matth. 16.18. <hi>And I ſay unto thee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and upon this rock <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> will build my Church, and the gates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hell ſhall not prevail againſt it.</hi> But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d S. <hi>Peters</hi> faith failed, the gates of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll had long ago no doubt prevailed.</p>
               <p>Matth. 23.2. <hi>The Scr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bes and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hariſes ſit in M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes ſeat, all therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hatſoever they bid you obſerve, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſerve and do.</hi> How could <hi>Chriſt</hi> bid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e people of the old Law, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ever he ſhold bid them, by thoſe that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32773:16"/>ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> chair, if they could err<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> But God hath no leſſe preſerved th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> truth of Chriſtian Religion, in the cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> which is in the new La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> anſwerable to that of <hi>Moſes</hi> in the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Therefore neither S. <hi>Peters</hi> Faith, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chair hath failed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> 11, 49, 51. Speaking of <hi>Caip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the High-prieſt, ſaith: <hi>And this he spa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> not of himſelf, but being High prieſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> year he propheſied, that Jeſus ſhould for that Nation.</hi> See, how in this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wicked time of the Sinagogue, the ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Dregs and out-caſt of that diſobedie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> people, yet ſpeaking forth of that Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> had commanded to heard and obeyed, touching matters faith, anſwer truly, and their chief ſhops propheſie.</p>
               <p>¶ So <hi>Leo ſer.</hi> 3. <hi>de aſſump. ſua</hi> affir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame: <hi>The danger was common all the Apoſtles, but our Lord took spe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> care of</hi> Peter, <hi>that the ſtate of all the might be more ſure, if the Head were vincible.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:32773:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>They affirm. VII.</hi> That the Church can err, and hath erred.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 59.21. <hi>As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or me, this is my Covenant with them, ſaith the Lord. My ſpirit that is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, and my words, which I have but in thy mouth, ſhall not depant out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eed, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeeds ſeed, from henceforth, and for ever.</hi> Therefore the Church cannot err.</p>
               <p>John 14.16. <hi>I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he may abide with you for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, even the ſpirit of truth.</hi> But the Apoſtles themſelves lived not for ever: therefore this is to be underſtood of the perpetual aboad of the ſpirit of truth with their Succeſſors.</p>
               <p>Matth. 18.17. <hi>And if he neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as an heathen man, and a Publican.</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:32773:17"/>Whence is clearly to be gathered, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Church in her Cenſure cannot er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 35.8. <hi>And a high way ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> there, and a way, and it ſhall be call the way of Holineſs, the unclean ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> not preſs over it, but it ſhall be for thoſe the waifaring men, though fools, ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> not err therein.</hi> How far deceive then are many ſimple ſouls, who do a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that the whole Church, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holy men that ever have been there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for theſe thouſand years (how wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſoever) have all erred.</p>
               <p>Epheſ. 5.27. <hi>That he might preſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it to himſelf a glorious Church, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> having ſpot, or wrincle, or any ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> thing, but that it ſhould be holy a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> without blemiſh.</hi> Note well theſe word <hi>without ſpot, wrincle, or any blemiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and tell me now if it be poſſible, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reading this, thou canſt ever believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that ſhe hath ever taught ſuch horrib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> blaſphemies and abominations, as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this day ſhe is charged with?</p>
               <p>See more <hi>John</hi> 16.13. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 37.26. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.3. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>John</hi> 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:32773:17"/>
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 10.25.29. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>John</hi> 10.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32. <hi>Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi> 4.5.11. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Malac.</hi> 27. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</p>
               <p>¶ The Fathers a firm the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly <hi>S. Aug. cont. Creſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. Alſo upon the 118. <hi>Iſal.</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e place begins: <hi>Ne auferas de ere meo verbum veritatis uſquequaque. S. Cypr. Epiſt.</hi> 55. <hi>ad Cornel. num.</hi> 3. <hi>S. Irenaeus lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. with many <hi>others.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>They affirm. VIII.</hi> That the Church hath been hidden and inviſible.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.14.15. <hi>Ye are the light of the world, a City that is ſet on a hill, cannot be hid. Neither do men light a candle, and put it under a buſhel, but on a candleſtick, and it giveth light to all that are in the houſe.</hi> But the Catholick Church is ſuch a light, ſuch a candle, and ſuch a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32773:18"/>City built upon <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mountain, therefore had not, nor ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be hidden, nor is inviſible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. <hi>Tell the Church, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> neglected to hear thee: but if he neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as a heathen man, and a Publican.</hi> Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it were a very hard caſe to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a Heathen, for not telling, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hearing a Church, which hath ſo cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lain hid, that no man could here ſee, feel, or underſtand it for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years.</p>
               <p>2 Cor. 4.3. <hi>But if our Goſpel be hia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is hid to them that are loſt.</hi> Loe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cenſure of S. <hi>Paul</hi> upon all ſuch as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that the Church, or her Goſpel ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be hid.</p>
               <p>Iſai. 2.2. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the laſt days, that the mountain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Lords houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the top of the mountains, and ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> exalted above the hills, and all nation ſhall flow unto it.</hi> In hundreds of place do the Propheſies mention this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Mich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 4.7. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which ſhould be all in vain
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32773:18"/>if this his kingdom could be inviſible; for a Propheſie muſt be of things, which may be ſeen and perceived by our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; otherwiſe every man might be a Prophet, and foretel of things to come, which if they ſhould not come to paſſe, he might anſwer, that they had come to paſs in very deed as he had propheſied, but that they were inviſible to the world. Lo the viſible abſurdities of this inviſible Church.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Pſa.</hi> 27.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 19.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 19.3, 4. <hi>Iſai</hi> 60.20. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.9.</p>
               <p>¶ The Fathers commonly affirmed the ſame. <hi>Origen. hom.</hi> 30. <hi>in Matth. The Church is full of light, even from the Eaſt to the Weſt.</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſtom. hom.</hi> 4. <hi>in.</hi> 6. <hi>of Iſai. It is eaſier for the ſun to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, then the Church to be darkned. S.</hi> Aug. <hi>tract. in John</hi> calls thoſe <hi>blinde, that do not ſee ſo great a mountain. S.</hi> Cyp. <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitate Eccleſiae, to the ſame purpoſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:32773:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>They maintain. IX.</hi> That the Church was not always to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Catholick or univerſal, and that the Church of Rome is not ſuch a Church.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2.8. <hi>Ask of me, and I ſhall gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e thee the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then for thine inheritance, and the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> And Luke 1.33. <hi>He ſhall reign over the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>for ever, and of his kingdom there ſhall be no end.</hi> But none of theſe promiſes have been any where elſe ſo much verified, as in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> therefore both the Church had been alwayes univerſal, &amp; the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> only ſuch a Church</p>
               <p>Coloſ. 1.3. &amp;c. <hi>We give thanks to God for you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Since we heard your faith,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For the hope which is laid up for you in heaven, whereof ye heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the word of the truth of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which is come unto you, as it is in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32773:19"/>all the world, and bringeth forth fruit, as it doth alſo in you, ſince the day, you heard of it, and knew the grace of God in truth.</hi> But no Faith, or Goſpel hath, or is, ſo dilated in all the world, nor hath fructified, and grown (for ſo we read) as the faith of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church hath done, as appears more plainly by this which follows.</p>
               <p>Rom. 1.8. <hi>Firſt I thank my God through</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>for you all, that your faith is ſpoken of throughout the whole world.</hi> Where in expreſs terms, <hi>S. Paul</hi> calls the faith of the whole world (or Catholick faith) the faith of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that is, of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Therefore the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and no other, is truly, and indeed ſuch a Church.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.32. <hi>Gon.</hi> 22.18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.46. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.4.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.8. (we 71.) <hi>Mark</hi> 16.20. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p>All which places are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, not that the whole world ſhould be Catholick at one and the ſame time,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32773:20"/>but that the whole ſhould be converted to <hi>Chriſt</hi> at ſundry times, and that it ſhold comprehend a greater part of the world, then any Sect of hereticks ſhold ever do: and this is the true ſenſe of being <hi>Catholick,</hi> or Univerſal.</p>
               <p>¶ And to follow ſtill our former Rule, hear the Fathers that affirm the ſame. <hi>S. Cypr. ep.</hi> 57. writing to <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius,</hi> Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaith: <hi>Whileſt with you there is one mind and one voice, the whole Church is confeſſed to be the Roman Church.</hi> S. Aug. de unitat. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. cap. 4. ſaith. <hi>Who ſo diſſent from the body of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>which is the Church, that they do not communicate with all the whole corps of Chriſtendom, certain it is, that they are not in the Catholick Church.</hi> S. <hi>Hierom</hi> in his Apologie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> and in other places, ſaith, that it is all one to ſay <hi>Roman faith, and the Catholick faith.</hi> Again, <hi>S. Aug.</hi> upon the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. (we 44.) but much more excellently <hi>in ep.</hi> 161. <hi>ad Honorat.</hi> The place begins: <hi>Dignere ergo reſcribere nobis.</hi> As alſo <hi>cont. lib. Petil. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:32773:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Reformers hold. X.</hi> That the Churches <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity is not neceſſary in all points of faith.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.5. <hi>One Lord, One Faith, One Baptiſm:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Unity is neceſſary in all points of faith. The reaſon is, for that the Church, being a Congregation of the faithful, one Faith is neceſſary to make one Church, but our Adverſaries differ in matters of faith, therefore they have not the Unity requiſite to one Church.</p>
               <p>James 2.10. <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all.</hi> And even ſo it is in our faith, for who ſo denies one Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle denies all.</p>
               <p>Acts 4.32. <hi>And the multitude of them that believed, were of one heart, and of one ſoul.</hi> And again 1 Cor. 1.10. <hi>New I beſeech you Brethren, by the name of our Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32773:21"/>that there be no diviſions among you, that ye be perfectly joyned together the ſame minde, and in the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Whereas our Adverſaries are a hundred ſeveral minds and judg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments, there being an infinity of Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> among them, without any the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhew of Unity; And therefore ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> not be the <hi>true believers</hi> mentioned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Jerem.</hi> 32.39. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.25. <hi>Mark.</hi> 24. <hi>Luk</hi> 11.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.19. <hi>Ephe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2.14, 15, 16.8.22. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.26, 27. <hi>Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 5.9. <hi>and</hi> 1.8. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.15. <hi>John.</hi> 1.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121.3.</p>
               <p>¶ And laſtly to check, by our com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon Rule, the breakers of this Uni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Rule, S. <hi>Aug.</hi> (eited by the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuduc. p.</hi> 134.) ſaith: <hi>In Cathedra un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tatis, poſuit Deus doctrinam verstatis</hi> In the chair of Unity, God hath place the Doctrine of verity. As alſo <hi>cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Par. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. The place begin <hi>Qui non vult ſedere,</hi> S. Cyprian <hi>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> de unitat. Eccleſ. nu.</hi> 3. ſaith: <hi>Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unity
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32773:21"/>of the Church, he that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldeth not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth he think he holds the faith;</hi> S. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilary lib. ad Conſtantinum Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um,</hi> and many others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XI</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat <hi>S. Peter</hi> was not ordained by <hi>Chriſt</hi> the firſt Head, or Chief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Apoſtles, and that among the twelve, none was greater, or leſſer than other.</head>
               <p>Contrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, Mat. 10.2. <hi>Now he names of the twelve Apoſtles are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heſe: The firſt</hi> Simon <hi>who is called Peter.</hi> All the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> do put <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> in the firſt place, and wicked <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> in the laſt. And wherefore this, but becauſe the one was firſt in dignity and worthieſt of the reſt; and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri wiſe; the other laſt, and unworthieſt of all his fellows? Again, why, as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is called <hi>Firſt,</hi> are not the reſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Second, Third &amp;c.</hi> But to ſhew thereby, that they did not therefore call <hi>Peter first,</hi> becauſe he occurred firſt to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32773:22"/>be named; but becauſe he was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> both in dignity and authority whom therefore they all number <hi>Firſt</hi> and call the <hi>Firſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mat. 16.18. <hi>And I ſay alſo un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>thee, that thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> reck I will build my Church, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it.</hi> Words clearly inſinuating S. <hi>Peter</hi> Supremacy in the Church of God; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> according to the Greek and Syria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> text (as our Doctors note) theſe words <hi>Thou art Peter,</hi> ſound thus: <hi>Thou ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Rock, and upon this Rock I will build my Church.</hi> So that, to ſay, that <hi>Peter</hi> is the rock of the Church, is as much, as to call him chief, or head of the Church.</p>
               <p>Neither without ſpecial myſtery, did our Lord impoſe upon him this new name, the name <hi>Peter</hi> (a Rock o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Stone) being one of the moſt excellent names of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is many times in holy Scripture, termed by the name of a Rock or Stone, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 117.22. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28.6. <hi>Dan.</hi> 24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.42. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.33. So that this Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, &amp; abſolute Paſtor of the Church,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:32773:22"/>did communicate this new name unto his Vicat, to repreſent the more lively the ſupreme authority, which he would give him over his flock.</p>
               <p>And note, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith not, <hi>I have built,</hi> or, <hi>I do build,</hi> but <hi>I will build;</hi> the Church being built upon himſelf from his Incarnation: and ſo as theſe words reſerred to <hi>Chriſt</hi> (as our <hi>Reformers</hi> uſe to do) do not well agree, to the building of the Church upon <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as head thereof for the time to come; but moſt fitly agree to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> as Head thereof, for the time to come.</p>
               <p>Matth. 16.19. <hi>And I will give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee the keys of the kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> &amp;c. By theſe words alſo, no leſs than by the former, is clearly ſignified <hi>S. Peters</hi> Supremacy. For none hath the government or commandement of the keys of any Town, or City, but the Prince, Governour, or Magiſtrates of the ſame. And that ſovereign Power ſignified by the <hi>Keyes,</hi> is likewiſe proved by that of our <hi>Saviour Chriſt: I have the keys of hell, and of death.</hi> Apoc. 1.18. <hi>As alſo by</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:32773:23"/>the key of <hi>David, which openeth, and no man ſhutteth, ſhutteth and no man openeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now add to this that hath been ſaid the correſpondency of the words of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Saviour</hi> to <hi>S. Peter,</hi> with the words of <hi>S. Peter</hi> again to him, and how clear will this doctrine appear? For when our Lord asked his diſciples <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Whom ſay ye that I am?</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded not, how they called his name<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which was <hi>Jeſus</hi> (for that they knew full well before) but what his quality, office, and dignity was? And <hi>S. Peter</hi> anſwering: <hi>Thou art</hi> Chriſt <hi>the Son of the living God,</hi> Jeſus told him not his Name (which was <hi>Simon</hi>) but gave him another name, and ſuch an one, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſignified the office, quality, and dignity, that he beſtowed upon him, ſaying: Thou art <hi>Cephas;</hi> or <hi>Petrus,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Rock</hi> or <hi>Peter.</hi> Therefore he ordained him <hi>Head,</hi> &amp;c,</p>
               <p>1 Cor. 3.4 22. <hi>For while one ſaith, I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>I am of</hi> Apollo, <hi>I of</hi> Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas, <hi>I of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See, how from thoſe he would have eſteemed leſſer, he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:32773:23"/>aſcends to thoſe whom he would have eſteemed greater, and placeth <hi>Peter</hi> next to <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Luke 22.31, 32. <hi>And the Lord ſaid,</hi> Simon, Simon, <hi>&amp;c. When thou art con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erted, ſtrengthen</hi> (we read <hi>confirm</hi>) <hi>thy b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ethren.</hi> Now what other things is it for <hi>Peter,</hi> to ſtrengthen (or confirm) his brethren, but to practiſe and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe his greatneſſe over them? For he that doth ſtrengthen (or confirm) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is the greater: and they who are ſtrengthened (or confirmed) are made thereby inferior to him, who doth ſtrengthen; (or confirm) them.</p>
               <p>Luke 22.26. <hi>He that is greateſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, let him be, as the yonger: and he that is the chief, as he that doth ſerve;</hi> Where the words, <hi>(He that is greateſt, is chief)</hi> do evidently ſhew, that amongſt the twelve, one was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than another, and was ſo accounted even by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf.</p>
               <p>John 21.15.16.17. Jeſus <hi>ſaid to</hi> Simon Peter: Simon <hi>loveſt thou me more than theſe? Feed my Lambs: feed my ſheep</hi> (where the Greek hath in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:32773:24"/>ſecond place for <hi>feed, govern</hi> or <hi>rule.</hi>) Hence it follows, that either the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were not accounted to be in the flock of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or elſe they were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> as to their head, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> commanded him to feed or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, not onely his <hi>Lambs</hi> (to wit, the lay people) but his ſheep alſo, that is, the Apoſtles and Paſtors themſelves: for beſides <hi>Lambs</hi> and <hi>Sheep,</hi> there is nothing in the Church of God. Again, if S. <hi>Peter</hi> loved our Lord more than all his fellow-Apoſtles did; it follows neceſſarily, that he received more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to feed, than all the reſt did. For it cannot be conceived, that he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to <hi>love,</hi> more than to <hi>feed:</hi> but he loveth more than others, therefore he is willed to feed more than the others; and conſequently, to be head of the others.</p>
               <p>Matth. 12.25, 26. <hi>Every kingdom divided againſt it ſelf, is brought to deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lation. And if Satan can caſt out Satan, &amp;c.</hi> Satan therefore hath a Kingdom, whereof he is the chief. If then there be not onely a viſible Head
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32773:24"/>of the Church triumphant in heaven, but alſo a viſible head even in hell; why not a viſible head alſo on earth?</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Pſa.</hi> 18, 43. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 45.16. (we 49.) <hi>Wark</hi> 2.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.33. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.5.</p>
               <p>¶ The Holy Fathers doe commonly affirm the ſame. <hi>Theophilactus</hi> in <hi>Luke</hi> 22. calls <hi>Peter</hi> Prince of the Diſciples. <hi>Euſebius in Chron.</hi> cals him the <hi>Firſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Chriſtians:</hi> S. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Hier. cat.</hi> 2. Prince and moſt excellent of all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. S. <hi>Chryſoſt. hom.</hi> 55. <hi>in Matth.</hi> Paſtor and head of the Church. <hi>Euthym. in cap. ult. John.</hi> Maſter of the whole world. S. <hi>Leo epiſt.</hi> 89. Head and chief of the Apoſtles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:32773:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>They alſo hold. XII.</hi> That a woman may he Head, or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governeſs of the Church in all cauſes, as the late Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth was.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 11.12. <hi>Let the woman learn in ſilence, with all ſubjection. But I ſuffer not a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to teach, nor to uſurpe authority over the man.</hi> Therefore a woman cannot be Head of the Church.</p>
               <p>1 Cor. 14.34. <hi>Let women hold their peace in the Churches, for it is not permitted them to ſpeak, but to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as all the Law ſaith,</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶ I produce no Fathers for diſproof of this point, for never was any woman ſo preſumptuous in our Fore-Fathers days, as to take upon her ſuch authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: but will content my ſelf to refute the folly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this evident and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing argument.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:32773:25"/>Whatſoever power an inferiour Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Church hath, that the head of the ſame Church hath, (at the leaſt) if not much more. But every inferiour Miniſter of their Church, hath power to Baptize, to give the Communion, to marry, to bury, and to preach in the Pulpit; Therefore Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> could Baptize, give the Communion, marry, bury, and preach in the Pulpit.</p>
               <p>And who now is ſo ſimple, as not to ſee the ridiculous ſequele of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? For the denial of which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, hundreds of Catholicks heve been hanged, drawn and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, as Traytors to her perſon, and the State.</p>
               <p>But that no ſecular King can be this Head, an infinity of Fathers do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, <hi>S. John Dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcen. ſer.</hi> 1. The place begins <hi>Tibi O Rex.</hi> And again. <hi>Non aſſentior: I conſent not that the Church of God be governed by Kings.</hi> Theod. <hi>hiſt. Eccleſ. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 28. makes mention of one <hi>Eulogius,</hi> who (being told by an officer of the Emperour <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens,</hi> that the Emperour would have it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:32773:26"/>ſo, anſwered thus, <hi>What? was he mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Biſhop that day that he was crowned Emperour?</hi> The place begins: <hi>Tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ille.</hi> S. <hi>Ignatius Epiſt. ad Philadelph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Wills all men without exception, ever the <hi>Emperour</hi> himſelf, to be obedient unto the Biſhop; the place begins, <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes obedite Caeſari.</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſt. hom.</hi> 5. <hi>de verhis Iſaiae</hi> calleth the Biſhop, a Prince as well as the King: yea, and that a greater alſo. And <hi>hom.</hi> 38. in <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. The place begins, <hi>Quia in rebus spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualibus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> That Antichriſt ſhall not be a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar man; and that the Pope is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, 2 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Let no man deceive you by any means, for that day ſhall not come, except there come a falling away firſt, and that man of ſin be revealed, the ſon of perdition.</hi> Where theſe words, <hi>man of ſin,</hi> and <hi>ſon of perdition,</hi> do plainly prove, that a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32773:26"/>of men (as the <hi>Popes</hi> are) cannot be this man of ſin: for ſo S. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo ſhould be <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> for he was <hi>Pope,</hi> &amp; the very firſt of all the <hi>Popes.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhal be a particular man.</p>
               <p>Rev. 13.18. <hi>Let him that hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding count the number of a man:</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the great <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> that egregious Apoſtata, or notable enemy of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſhall be a particular man.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>John</hi> 2.22. <hi>Who is a liar, but he that denieth that</hi> Jeſus is Chriſt? <hi>This is</hi> Antichriſt, <hi>which denieth the Father, and the ſon.</hi> But the <hi>Pope</hi> denieth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of both: Therefore the <hi>Pope</hi> is not <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again in 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. Before alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. The Scripture ſaith, that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall be extolled above all that is called God: and <hi>verſe</hi> 8. That our <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> ſhall kill him with the ſpirit of his mouth at his coming: But none of all theſe agree to the <hi>Pope,</hi> no more than that our <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> is come the ſecond time.</p>
               <p>John 5.43. <hi>I am come in my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers name, and ye receive me not: if
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32773:27"/>another ſhall come in his own name, him ye will receive.</hi> He means eſpecially the wicked <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> how then can the <hi>Pope</hi> be he, ſeeing the Jews receive him not?</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.7. <hi>and cap.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.17. and <hi>cap.</hi> 17.8, 11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.15.</p>
               <p>¶ To follow our common Rule, the Fathers that affirm the ſame are S. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> and S. <hi>Cyril.</hi> who do both thus underſtand this very place laſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged. S. <hi>Amb.</hi> upon the 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Hier. in ep. ad Algas. quaeſt.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. S. <hi>Aug.</hi> 29. <hi>tract. in Joan.</hi> S. <hi>Irenaeus. l.</hi> 5. <hi>cont. hereſ. Valentin. Theodoret</hi> in his epitome of the divine decrees, <hi>cap. de Antichriſto.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> That no man, nor any but God, can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, or retain ſins.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>John</hi> 20.21. <hi>As my Father hath ſent me, even ſo ſend I you.</hi> Now <hi>Chriſt</hi> was ſent by his Father, not onely to Teach, Preach, Adminiſter Sacraments, and to work
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32773:27"/>miracles; but alſo to forgive ſins: but the Diſciples were ſent with power to Teach, Preach, Adminiſter Sacraments and to work miracles: Therefore alſo to forgive ſins.</p>
               <p>Ibid. verſ. 22.23. <hi>When he had ſaid this, he breathed on them, and ſaid unto them. Receive ye the holy Ghoſt: whoſe ſins ye remit, they are remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them, and whoſe ſins ye retain, they are retained. Chriſt</hi> having firſt ſhewed his own commiſſion, which was to pardon ſins, preſently gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth his Apoſtles power to do the ſame, breathing upon them the holy Ghoſt. He therefore that denieth man to have his power, either denieth that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt can forgive ſins, or that <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave not his Diſciples the holy Ghoſt to this end and purpoſe: both which are clearly falſe, and againſt the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
               <p>Mat. 9.3.8. <hi>but when the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſaw it, they marvelled, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied God who had given ſuch power un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men,</hi> as to forgive ſins. Which though they knew to appertain to God onely
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32773:28"/>by nature, yet they perceived that it might be done by mans miniſtry on earth, to the glory of God. Yea, thoſe who affirm God onely ſo to remit ſins that the miniſterial power thereof can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be communicated to men; deny the one part of <hi>Chriſt</hi> diſtinct, or double manner of remitting of ſins, to wit, only in heaven and not in earth.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19. <hi>and Mat.</hi> 18.1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10.2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Num.</hi> 5.6.</p>
               <p>¶ The ancient Fathers, who affirm the ſame, are S. <hi>Aug. tract.</hi> 49. <hi>in Joan.</hi> And in his book of fifty homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies <hi>hom.</hi> 9. <hi>S. Chriſoſt, de ſacerdotio l.</hi> 3. <hi>S. Amb. l.</hi> 3. <hi>de poenitentia, S. Cyril. l.</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 50. <hi>in Joan</hi> ſaith: <hi>It is abſurd, that they ſhould remit mans ſins who have not in them the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, Baſil. l.</hi> 5. <hi>cont. Eunom.</hi> Proves the holy Ghoſt to be God (which that deteſtable Heretick deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) becauſe he forgiveth ſins by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. S. <hi>Irenaeus l.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>S. Greg. hom.</hi> 6. <hi>in Evang.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:32773:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XV.</hi> That we ought not to confeſs our ſins to any man, but to God onely.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.5.6. <hi>Then went out to him</hi> (to wit, to S. John Baptiſt) <hi>Hieruſalem, and all Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and were baptized of him in Jordan, confeſſing their ſins.</hi> Not by acknowledging themſelves, but every man to utter, and tell his particular and ſecret ſins. Therefore we may confeſſe our ſins, not onely to God but alſo to man.</p>
               <p>Acts 19.18.19. <hi>And many that believed, came and confeſſed, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their deeds</hi> (behold confeſſion) <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny alſo of them which uſed curious Arts, brought their books together, and burned them before all men: and they counted the price of them, and found it five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pieces of ſilver</hi> (behold Satisſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) Therefore we may confeſſe our ſins to man.</p>
               <p>Num. 5, 6. <hi>When a man, or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhall commit any ſin that men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Then they ſhall confeſſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32773:29"/>their ſin, which they have done,</hi> &amp;c. And that this is not underſtood to be confeſſed to God in heaven, but allſo to his Prieſt on earth, the whole Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, from <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. unto the end, doth clearly teſtifie. Adde hereto, that he ſaith not, <hi>they ſhall confeſſe their ſins</hi> (to wit, in general) but <hi>their ſin,</hi> to wit in particular.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.4. <hi>James</hi> 5.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.14.</p>
               <p>¶ See the holy Fathers that affirm the ſame. S. <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Tertul. l. de poenitentia,</hi> where he reprehend's ſome, who for humane ſhamefaſtneſs neglected to go to confeſſion. It is written of S. <hi>Amb.</hi> that he himſelf ſate to hear confeſſions, <hi>Amb. ex Paulino</hi> S. <hi>Clement</hi> S. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſours, ſpeaks wonderfully pithily to this purpoſe, <hi>ep. ad fratr. Dom.</hi> But of all others <hi>Origen</hi> is moſt plain for this point. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Periar. S. Chryſ. l.</hi> 3. <hi>de Sacerd. &amp; hom.</hi> 85. <hi>in Joan. S. Aug.</hi> cited as before. S. <hi>Amb. oret. in muliere peccatrice</hi> ſaith, <hi>Confeſſe freely to the Prieſt the hidden ſecrets of thy ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:32773:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> That Pardons, and Indulgences, were not in the Apoſtles times.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. <hi>To whom ye forgive any thing, I forgive alſo: for if I forgave any thing to whom I forgave it, for your ſake forgave I it, in the perſon of</hi> Chriſt. The <hi>Corinthian</hi> aforeſaid, was excommunicated, and put to penance by the Apoſtle, as plainly appeareth 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3. and here in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. cited above, he giveth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for his pardon. A plain proof of the Apoſtles power, there of binding, here of looſing, there of puniſhing, here of pardoning. Therefore pardons were in uſe in the Apoſtles times.</p>
               <p>2 Cor. 2.6. <hi>Sufficient to ſuch a man, is this puniſhment</hi> (or Cenſure) <hi>which was inflicted of many.</hi> Whence it is clear, that it lieth in the hands of the ſpiritual Magiſtrates, to meaſure the time of ſuch puniſhment, or penance impoſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:32773:30"/>See more <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.18. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.19.</p>
               <p>¶ As alſo the Fathers that affirm the ſame. <hi>Tertul. lib. ad Mart. cap.</hi> 1.5. <hi>S. Syp. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ep.</hi> 15. <hi>and ſerm. de lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis. Concil. Lateran. Can.</hi> 62. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of <hi>Innocentius</hi> 3. <hi>and</hi> 4. <hi>de poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. and remiſ. cap. Quod autem. S. Amb. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de poenit. cap.</hi> 2. the place begins; <hi>Dominus per jus. S. Aug. ep.</hi> 75. <hi>ad Auxil. Epiſcop.</hi> The place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, <hi>ſpiritualis poena. S. Chryſoſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>de ſacerdot.</hi> The place begins, <hi>Si rex a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquis.</hi> Laſtly Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 2. gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a plenary Indulgence to ſuch, as went unto the Holy War.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Proteſtants hold. XVII.</hi> That the actions, and paſſions of the Saints, do ſerve for nothing to the Church.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.24. <hi>I now rejoyce in my ſufferings for you, and fill up that which is behinde</hi> (we read, <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi>) <hi>of the afflictions of</hi> Chriſt <hi>in my
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32773:30"/>fleſh for his bodies ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke, which is the Church.</hi> Hence hath ground been always taken of Indulgences (but much more principally, from the ſuper abundant merit of Jeſus Chriſt;) There the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and paſſions of the Saints, do ſerve for ſomething to the Church.</p>
               <p>Philip. 2.30. <hi>Becauſe for the work of Chriſt, he was nigh unto death, not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his life, to ſupply your lack of ſervice towards me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Contrary alſo to an Article of our Creed, <hi>I beleeve the Communion of Saints.</hi> For to what purpoſe believe we this, If their actions and paſſions may not be imparted to us, nor ſerve to any purpoſe to the Church?</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.63. (we 118.) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 53. (we 52.) 9.2. <hi>Mac.</hi> 15.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.3. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.30, 31. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.52. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.5. <hi>and</hi> 48.16. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.13. <hi>Job</hi> 5.1. <hi>Hier.</hi> 15.1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.35. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14.36. <hi>Luke</hi> 8.44. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.15.</p>
               <p>All theſe paſſages contain actions, or prayers of the Church triumphant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the militant or p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tient, or for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32773:31"/>both, I care not which they grant, and yet one they muſt needs confeſſe.</p>
               <p>¶ See the Fathers that affirm the ſame, S. <hi>August. lib. de cura promort. cap.</hi> 2. The place begins: <hi>Etſi nuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam.</hi> And again the ſame Saints in the ſame book, S. <hi>Maximus ſer. de ſanctis Octavio &amp; Adventio,</hi> the place begins, <hi>Cuncti Martyres.</hi> S. <hi>Bede hiſt. Eccleſ. Angliae, l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. S. <hi>Aug. in Pfa.</hi> 61. the place begins, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus enim homo:</hi> as alſo S. <hi>Anſelm</hi> upon the ſame <hi>Pſalm.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVIII.</hi> That no man can do works of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>errogation.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21. <hi>If thou wilt be perfect, go and ſell that thou haſt, and give to the poor, and thou ſhalt have treaſure in heaven, and come and follow me.</hi> Hence it plainly appears, that man, by the aſſiſtance of Gods grace, may do ſome things coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled, which are of more perfection then the things commanded: and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32773:31"/>theſe we call, <hi>Works of Supererrogation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 Cor. 7.25. <hi>Now concerning Virgins, I have no Commandement of the Lord, yet I give my judgement</hi>) we reade <hi>Counſel</hi>) <hi>as one that hath obtained mercy of the Lord to be faithful.</hi> And <hi>verſe</hi> 38. <hi>He that giveth her in marriage doth well, but he that giveth her not in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage doth better.</hi> To do that which is counſelled is not neceſſary, becauſe one may nevertheleſſe be ſaved: but he who omits what is commanded (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he do pennance) cannot eſcape e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal pains.</p>
               <p>Matt. 19.12. <hi>There be Eunuchs which have made themſelves Eunuchs for the kingdom of heaven, he that is able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it</hi> (we reade <hi>take it</hi>) <hi>let him receive it.</hi> But this cannot properly be ſaid of precepts, as S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> noteth upon this place, <hi>ſer.</hi> 61. <hi>de temp.</hi> for of precepts it is not ſaid, keep them <hi>who is able,</hi> but keep them <hi>abſolutely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See more <hi>Luke</hi> 10.25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.44. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.34.</p>
               <p>¶ And the holy Fathers affirm the ſame, S. <hi>Ambr. l. de viduit. Origan in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32773:32"/>which we do over and above our duty, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb.</hi> 1. <hi>Demonſtrat. cap.</hi> 8. <hi>S. Chryſoſt. hom.</hi> 8. <hi>de act. poenit. Blame not our Lord, he commandeth nothing impoſſible; yea, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do no more then they are commanded. S. Greg. Nicen.</hi> 1. <hi>Moral. cap</hi> 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> That by the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> we have all loſt our Free-will, and that it is not in our power to chooſe good, but onely evil.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 37. <hi>He that ſtandeth ſtedfaſt in his heart, having no neceſſity, but hath power over his own will, and hath ſo decreed in his heart, that he will keep his virgin, doth well.</hi> But if a man have not freedom of will, as well to the one as to the other, why doth the holy Ghoſt (<hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26.) require of us to <hi>give him our heart,</hi> if we cannot conſent but unto evil? Therefore it is in our power to chooſe good or evil.</p>
               <p>John 1.11, 12. <hi>He came unto his own, and his own received him not: but as many as received him, to them gave
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:32773:32"/>he power to become the ſons of God;</hi> words which plainly imply a liberty of will: For when he ſaith, <hi>ſome received him, and ſome not,</hi> who ſees not the libetty both of the one, and of the other; for theſe would not receive him, and thoſe would.</p>
               <p>Deut. 30.19. <hi>I call heaven and earth to record this d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y againſt you, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t I have ſet before you life and death, bleſſing and curſing, therefore chooſe life, that both thou, and thy ſeed may live.</hi> And right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may we call heaven and earth to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt them, who commit the ſame fault touching Grace, which the <hi>Turks</hi> do touching Nature, For the <hi>Turks</hi> believe that the fire burns not, nor water wets not, but that God doth it, by the fire and water. And ſo our adverſaries ſay, that a man deſireth no good, nor doth no good, but only that God doth all by man: but this is falſe. Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Luke 13.34. <hi>O Hieruſalem, Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>How often would I have gathered thy children together, as a Hen doth gather her brood under her
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:32773:33"/>wings, and ye would not.</hi> I would, (ſaith Chriſt) and ye would not. What, for <hi>Gods</hi> ſake, can be ſpoken more plainly?</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Luke</hi> 10.42. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Ad Philem. verſe</hi> 14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.37. <hi>and</hi> 9.1.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 3.9. <hi>Num.</hi> 30.14. <hi>Joſua</hi> 14.13. 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 24.12. 3 <hi>Reg.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 15.15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 24.15. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11, 24. <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i</hi> 1.19, 20.</p>
               <p>¶ See the ancient Fathers, <hi>Euſ. Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar. de praep. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. ſaith, that thoſe who hold this opinion, do pervert and overthrow, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſam vitam huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, all the whole life of man.</hi> And in very deed his reaſon is good, for upon this conſideration of mans free-will, are grounded all politicall laws, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and prohibitions, pains and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, which elſe were meerly ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and againſt reaſon. S. <hi>Hilary,</hi> 1. <hi>Trinitate,</hi> ſaith: <hi>He would not there ſhould be a neceſſity for men to be the Sons of God, but a power.</hi> S. <hi>Aug. l</hi> 1. ad Simpl. <hi>q.</hi> 4. ſaith: <hi>To conſent, or not to conſent unto Gods vocation, lieth in a mans own will.</hi> So teacheth
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32773:33"/>S. <hi>Ambr. in Luke cap.</hi> 12. S. <hi>Chryſoſt. hom.</hi> 19. <hi>in Geneſ.</hi> S. <hi>Irenaeus l.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. S. <hi>Cyril. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>in Joan. cap.</hi> 7. <hi>We cannot in any wiſe deny freedome of will in man.</hi> And S. <hi>Aug.</hi> afore-cited, ſaith, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>de Act. cum Felic. Manich. How ſhould our Saviour reward every one according to their works, if there were no free-will.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XX.</hi> That it is impoſſible to keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God, though aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Grace, and the holy Ghoſt.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. <hi>I can do all things, through Christ that ſtrengthneth me.</hi> Therefore it is poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to keep the Commandments, or elſe it is falſe, that he could do all things.</p>
               <p>Luke 1.5, 6. The Scripture ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſaith: <hi>And they were both righteous before God, walking in all the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32773:34"/>and ordinances of the Lord, blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</hi> Yet Proteſtants uſually ſay, that none are ſo righteous as that they can keep any of them: but theſe two were ſo righteous as they kept all of them: now whether of theſe wilt thou believe S. <hi>Luke</hi> or our Reformers?</p>
               <p>Luke 11.27, 28. <hi>Bleſſed is the womb that bare thee, and the paps which thou haſt ſucked. But he ſaid; Yea, rather bleſſed are they that hear the Word of God, and keep it.</hi> Chriſt pronounceth them bleſſed, who hear the word of God and keep it: but the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are the word of God, (which they affirm no man can keep) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they affirm that no man can be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And like unto this is that of <hi>John</hi> 13.17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.50. <hi>John</hi> 14.23. With an infinite number of ſuch like places, in their own Bible: all which this their falſe doctrine doth in plain terms con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict.</p>
               <p>Luke 11.2. <hi>Thy will be done as in heaven, ſo in earth.</hi> In this petition, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we demand a thing impoſſible; or elſe the Saints in Heaven fulfil not the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:32773:34"/>will of God in all things; elſe it may be fulfilled alſo by us on earth, (one of the three) But the two firſt are great abſurdities; therefore the latter is to be granted.</p>
               <p>1 John 5.3. <hi>For this is the love of God, that we keep his commandements, and his commandements are not grievous.</hi> If the commandements were impoſſible, they could bind no man: for it is not to be conceived how one ſhould ſin in a thing, which he could not poſſibly avoid. And (if this were admitted) <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaying to the young man in the Goſpel: <hi>If thou wilt enter into heaven, keep the commandements,</hi> were as much as if he had ſaid; If thou wilt enter into heaven, take hold of the Moon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thy teeth.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36.27. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.30. <hi>and</hi> 19.17. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 15.15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8.10. <hi>and</hi> 73. <hi>Joſua</hi> 11.15. <hi>and</hi> 22.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.3. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.11.1. <hi>John</hi> 2.4. <hi>Job.</hi> 27.6. <hi>and</hi> 1.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.27. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.28 &amp;c. 15.7.3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 14.8. <hi>and</hi> 15.5. <hi>Ephſ.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:32773:35"/>¶ See <hi>Origen. hom.</hi> 9. <hi>in Joſue.</hi> S. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril l.</hi> 4. <hi>cont. Julian.</hi> S. <hi>Hilar. in Pſal.</hi> 118. S. <hi>Hier. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cont. Pelag.</hi> S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> who ſaith: <hi>It is an impious thing to ſay, that the commandements of God are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>They maintain. XXI.</hi> That faith onely juſtifieth; and that good Works are not abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.2. <hi>And though I have the gift of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, and underſtand all miſteries, and all knowledge; and although I have all faith ſo that I could remove moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and have no charity, I am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> Therefore faith onely doth not juſtifie: yet, this plainly proves that faith is nothing to ſalvation, without good works.</p>
               <p>James 2.24. <hi>Ye ſee therefore how that by works a man is juſtified, and not by faith onely.</hi> Wherefore S. <hi>Aug.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:32773:35"/>lib. de fide &amp; operibus, cap.</hi> 14. writes, that this Hereſie, was an old Hereſie, even in the Apoſtles times. And in the preface of his <hi>comment. upon the</hi> 32. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> He warns all men, that this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction upon this ſpeech of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Abraham <hi>was juſtified by faith, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore works be not neceſſary to ſalvation,</hi> is the right way to hell and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. See the <hi>Rhemes</hi> Teſtament upon this place.</p>
               <p>Jac. 2.14. <hi>What doth it profit my brethren, though a man ſay, he hath faith, and not works? Can faith ſave him?</hi> This propoſition (but eſpecially the former) is directly oppoſite to that which our Adverſaries hold. Neither can they pretend, that there is the like oppoſition or contradiction, betwixt S. <hi>James</hi> ſpeeches and S. <hi>Pauls:</hi> for though S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>Man is juſtified by faith,</hi> yet he never ſaith, <hi>by faith only.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gal. 5 6. <hi>For in</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>neither Circumciſion, availeth any thing, nor uncircumciſion, but faith which work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve.</hi> Note well this place: for if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u Adverſaries (who pretend Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32773:36"/>of places, to be the onely Rule to explicate the hard paſſages of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture) had followed but this their own Rule, this one text would have cleared unto them all other, wherein Juſtice and ſalvation might ſeem to be attributed to faith alone.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21, 22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.17. <hi>and</hi> 11.26. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.33. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. 1. <hi>Joan</hi> 2.4. 1. <hi>Joan.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <p>¶ The Fathers that affirm this are, <hi>Origen in</hi> 5. <hi>Rom. S. Hilar. cap.</hi> 7. <hi>in Mat. And S. Ambr. in</hi> 4. <hi>ad Heb.</hi> ſaith: <hi>Faith alone ſufficeth not. S. Aug. de fide &amp; operibus cap.</hi> 51. ſaith: <hi>I ſee not, why Chriſt ſhould ſay.</hi> If thou wilt have life everlaſting, keep the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, <hi>if without obſerving of them, by onely Faith, one might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXII.</hi> That no good Works are meritorious.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.17. <hi>For
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:32773:36"/>the Son of man ſhall come in the glory of his Father, with his Angels, and then he ſhall reward every man according to his works.</hi> He ſaith not that he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward every man according to his <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> or their <hi>faith,</hi> So S. <hi>Auguſt. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Apoſt. ſerm.</hi> 35. doth interpret.</p>
               <p>Mat. 5.12. <hi>Rejoyce and be glad, for great is your reward in heaven.</hi> The word <hi>Reward,</hi> in <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> ſignifieth <hi>wages</hi> and <hi>hire,</hi> due for works, and ſo preſuppoſeth a meritorious deed, as the <hi>Rhemiſh</hi> Teſtament noteth upon this place.</p>
               <p>Again Mat. 10.42. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall give to drink, a cup of cold water onely, in the name of a Diſciple, verily, I ſay unto you, he ſhall in no wiſe loſe his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> Therefore good works are meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious.</p>
               <p>2 Cor. 5.10. <hi>For we muſt all appear before the judgement ſeat of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>that every one may receive the things in his body, according to that he hath done, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be good, or bad;</hi> Words moſt clear, that Heaven is as well the reward of good works, as hell is the ſtipend of evil
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:32773:37"/>Therefore they muſt needs be enemies of a good life, and of all good works, who teach the contrary.</p>
               <p>See more 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 19.17. <hi>and</hi> 18.25 <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. <hi>and</hi> 3.8. 2. <hi>Eſdras</hi> 15.19. <hi>Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 16.6. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.4. <hi>and</hi> 22.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 26. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.9. <hi>and</hi> 6.38. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31.16. <hi>Sap.</hi> 5.16. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.21.</p>
               <p>¶ The holy Fathers unanimouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the ſame, <hi>S. Amb de apolog. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid cap.</hi> 6. <hi>S. Hier. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cont. Pelag. S. Aug. de ſpiritu</hi> &amp; <hi>lit. cap. ult. and</hi> others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIII.</hi> That faith once had, cannot poſſibly be loſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible,</hi> Luke <hi>8.13.</hi> They on the rock, are they, which when they hear, receive the word with joy, which for a while believe, and in the time of tentation fall away. <hi>Therefore faith once had, may afterwards be loſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:32773:37"/>
                  <hi>1</hi> Tim. <hi>1.18.19.</hi> This charge I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto thee, Son <hi>Timothy,</hi> according to the propheſies which went before on thee, that thou by them, mighteſt war a good warfare, holding faith and a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which ſome having put away, concerning faith have made ſhipwrack. <hi>Both which places do plainly reprove this falſe doctrine.</hi> That no man can fall from the faith, which he once truly had.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 2.16. &amp;c.</hi> Shun profane and vain bablings, for they will increaſe unto more ungodlineſs. And their word will eat as doth a canker, of whom is <hi>Hymeneus,</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the truth have erred, ſaying, that the reſurrection is paſt already, and overthrow the faith of ſome. <hi>If faith once had could not be loſt, this ſaying of the Apoſtle ſhould be falſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>See more 1</hi> Tim. <hi>6.20.</hi> Rev. <hi>2.5.</hi> Luke <hi>19.24.</hi> Matth. <hi>23.8.,</hi> &amp;c. Rom. <hi>11 20.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶ <hi>The Fathers affirm the ſame fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, and among the reſt</hi> S. Auguſt. de gratia <hi>&amp;</hi> lib. de correp. <hi>&amp;</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:32773:38"/>gratia, <hi>&amp;</hi> ad articulo falſo impoſitos. concil. Trid. leſſ. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>9.12.13. and others.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>They maintain. XXIV.</hi> That God by his will, and inevitable Decree, hath ordained from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, who ſhall be damned, and who ſaved.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3, 4. <hi>God our Saviour, who will have all men to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the truth.</hi> Meaning, by his conditional will, that is to ſay, if men will themſelves, by accepting, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or having done all things requiſite by Gods Law: for God uſeth not his abſolute will, or power towards us in this caſe. Therefore he hath not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and inevitably decreed any at all to be damned, as our Adverſaries hold.</p>
               <p>2 Pet. 3.9. <hi>The Lord is not ſlack concerning his promiſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that any ſhould periſh, but that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32773:38"/>all ſhould come to repentance,</hi> Therefore he is farre from ever making any ſuch decree, as our Adverſaries would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us.</p>
               <p>Wiſdom 1.13. <hi>For God made not death, neither hath he pleaſure in the destruction of the living.</hi> The reaſons, which conclude this truth, are manifeſt; for we muſt aſſure nothing of thoſe things, which depend upon the onely will of God, without clear and evident revelation. But predeſtination is ſuch. Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See more <hi>Oſe</hi> 13.9. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.32. <hi>Wiſ.</hi> 11.24. <hi>Joan.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20.32. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.9. <hi>and</hi> 28.14. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. <hi>and</hi> 9.27. <hi>and</hi> 10.12. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Job</hi> 9.2. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.14. <hi>Ionas</hi> 3.9. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.20. <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.9. 2 <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p>¶ See the Fathers that affirm the ſame in particular, S. <hi>Aug. l.</hi> 1. <hi>civit. Tertul. orat. c.</hi> 8. S. <hi>Cypr. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>epist.</hi> 2. <hi>And</hi> S. <hi>Amb. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Cain and Abel, will not that we refer unto God the prevari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> Adam, <hi>or the treaſon of</hi> Judas, <hi>though he knew the ſin before it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:32773:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Further they hold. XXV.</hi> They every one ought <hi>infallibly</hi> to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure himſelf of his Salvation, and to believe, that he is of the number of the Predeſtinate.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>9.27.</hi> I keep under my body, and bring it into ſubjection, leſt that by any means, when I have preached to others, I my ſelf ſhould be a cast away. <hi>A man would think, that S.</hi> Paul <hi>might be as ſure, and as confident of Gods grace and ſalvation, as any one of our Proteſtants be; and yet you ſee he durſt not adhere unto their preſumptuous, and unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſecurity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom. 11. 20 21.</hi> Thou standeſt by faith, be not high minded, but fear, for if God ſpared not the natural branches, take heed leſt he alſo ſpare not thee. Behold therefore the goodneſs and ſeverity of God, on them which fell, ſeverity; but towards thee good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:32773:39"/>if thou continue in his goodneſs, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe thou alſo ſhalt be cut off.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> Philip. <hi>2.12.</hi> Work out your own ſalvation, with fear and trembling. <hi>Moſt plain forcible places againſt the vain ſecurity of ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>See more,</hi> Prov. <hi>28.14.</hi> Eccleſ. <hi>9.1, 2. 2</hi> Tim. <hi>2.15. 2</hi> Pet. <hi>1.10.</hi> Tob. <hi>12.2. 13.</hi> Prov. <hi>20.9.</hi> Eccleſ. <hi>5.5.</hi> Iob <hi>9.20.</hi> Pſa. <hi>18.13. 1</hi> Cor. <hi>4.4.</hi> Deut. <hi>4.29. 2</hi> Cor. <hi>10.18. 1</hi> Pet. <hi>1.17.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶ <hi>See S.</hi> Amb. ſer <hi>5.</hi> in Pſa. <hi>118. S.</hi> Baſil in conſtit. monaſt. c. <hi>2.</hi> S. Hier. l. <hi>2.</hi> adverſ. Pelagianos, &amp; l. <hi>3.</hi> in Ierem. cap. <hi>13.</hi> S. Chryſoſt. hom. <hi>87.</hi> in Ioan. <hi>And S.</hi> Aug. in Pſa. <hi>40. ſaith:</hi> I know full well that the juſtice of my God remaineth; Whether my own juſtice remain or no, I know not; for the Apostle terrifieth me, ſaying. He that thinketh himſelf to ſtand, let him take heed lest he fall: <hi>S.</hi> Bern. ſer. <hi>3.</hi> de Adven. &amp; ſer. <hi>1.</hi> de Septuageſ. <hi>ſaith,</hi> Who can ſay, I am one of the Elect, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:32773:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVI.</hi> That every man hath not an Angel-Guardian, or keeper.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.10. <hi>Take heed that ye deſpiſe not one of theſe little ones; for I ſay unto you, that in heaven, their Angels do always behold the face of my Father, which is in heaven.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have their Angel-keeper. A thing ſo plain, that <hi>John Calvin</hi> durſt not deny it, although he would ſeem to make a doubt of it. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Inſtit. cap.</hi> 14. <hi>ſect.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Pſa. 91. (we 90) 11, 12. <hi>He ſhall give his Angels charge over thee, to keep thee in all thy ways; they ſhall bear thee up in their hands, leſt thou daſh thy foot againſt a ſtone.</hi> This very paſſage, <hi>S. Cyril of Alexandria lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cont. Iulian,</hi> applieth to our Angel-keeper.</p>
               <p>Acts 12.13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> knocking at the door, they ſaid, <hi>It is his Angel.</hi> Lo, how apparently the faith of the primitive Church appeareth concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this point.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:32773:40"/>See more, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Zachary</hi> 3.10. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.10. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.22. <hi>Tob.</hi> 5.15.20. <hi>Tob.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Tob.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.23. <hi>Joſhue</hi> 5.13. <hi>Nun.</hi> 22.22.31. <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.40. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.22.</p>
               <p>¶ See S. <hi>Greg. dial.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 58. <hi>S. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſ. do communi Eſſentia. S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. hom.</hi> 3. <hi>in ep. ad Coloſ. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerd. Greg. Turonenſ. lib. de gloria. mart.</hi> S. <hi>Aug. ep. ad Probam cap.</hi> 9. <hi>and epiſt.</hi> 69. <hi>ad fratres in eremo lib.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 31. <hi>civit.</hi> S. <hi>Hier.</hi> upon theſe words, <hi>Their Angels,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.10. teacheth; <hi>That it is a great dignity, and marvelous benefit, that every one hath from his nativity, an Angel for his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody and patronage.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVII.</hi> That the holy Angels pray not for us, nor know our thoughts, and deſires on earth.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible, <hi>Zachary</hi> 1.9.10.11.12. <hi>Then the Angel of the Lord anſwered and ſaid, O Lord of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:32773:41"/>Hoſts, how long wilt thou not have mercy on</hi> Hieruſalem, <hi>and on the Cities of</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, <hi>againſt which thou haſt had indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion theſe threeſcore, and ten years,</hi> And what, I pray you, is a prayer, if this be not? Therefore the holy Angels pray for us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tob.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Now therefore, when thou didſt pray, and</hi> Sarah <hi>thy daughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in-law, I did bring the remembrance of your prayers before the holy One.</hi> He who pleaſeth to read the whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſhall clearly ſee the manifold bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits beſides this one, which men receive at the hands of Angels: for which ſee the Annotations of the Catholick Bible upon this place.</p>
               <p>Revel. 8.4. <hi>And the ſmoke of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſes of the prayers of the Saints, aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the hand of the Angel before God.</hi> What can be poſſibly ſpoken more plain, to prove that Angels offer up prayers before God? yea this very place is ſo underſtood by S. <hi>Irenaeus l.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 34. towards the end.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.18.19.20. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.20. <hi>Acts.</hi> 5.19.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:32773:41"/>¶ See alſo S. <hi>Hilary</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 129. who ſaith: <hi>The interceſſion of Angels Gods nature needeth not, but our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity doth. S.</hi> Amb. <hi>lib. de viduis. Victor. utic. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de perſecut. Vandal.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVIII.</hi> That we may not pray to them.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.16. <hi>The Angel which redeemed me</hi> (we read, <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered me</hi>) <hi>from all evil, bleſs theſe lads,</hi> &amp;c. Here ſome perhaps will ſay, that this was God, and not an Angel. This is but a ſorry ſhift; for God had not then redeemed man, but long after. Yea this very paſſage is applyed by S. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> to our Angel-Gardian <hi>hom.</hi> 3. <hi>upon the</hi> 1. <hi>to the Coloſ.</hi> And by <hi>S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom.</hi> upon the 66. of <hi>Iſa.</hi> Alſo S. <hi>Baſil. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cont. Eunom.</hi> affirmeth, that this was ſpoken of a true Angel, and not of God: which being ſo, who can with reaſon ſay he prayed not unto him?</p>
               <p>Tob. 5.16. <hi>And when his ſon, had prepared all things for the journey,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:32773:42"/>his father ſaid, Go thou with this man, and God which dwelleth in heaven pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper your journey, and the Angel of God keep you company.</hi> Both God is here prayed unto, and his Angel alſo at the ſame inſtant, ſaying, <hi>God proſper you in your journey, and the Angel of God keep you company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oſe 12.4. <hi>Yea, he had power over the Angel, and prevailed; he wept, and made ſupplication unto him.</hi> Lo, what is plain, if this be not, for proof of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the bleſſed Angels?</p>
               <p>But ſome perhaps will ſay; I could be perſwaded to pray to Angels, if I could aſſure my ſelf that they could hear me, and knew what paſſeth here on earth. To this I anſwer likewiſe out of their own Bible, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.10. <hi>There is joy in the preſence of the Angels of God over one ſinner that repenteth.</hi> Now what more plain then that the Angels in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven know what we do on earth; which if they did not, how could they tejoyce at the converſion of a ſinner? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may pray lawfully unto them.</p>
               <p>See more, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.4. <hi>Song of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:32773:42"/>three Children verſ.</hi> 36. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.8. <hi>Num.</hi> 22.34. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.18.19.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.2.</p>
               <p>¶ S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> expounding thoſe words of <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.21. <hi>Have pitty upon me, have pitty upon me, O ye my friends, for the hand of God hath touched me,</hi> ſaith expreſly, that holy <hi>Iob addreſſed them to the Angels.</hi> As alſo thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Iob</hi> 5.1. <hi>Call now, if there be any that will anſwer thee,</hi> &amp;c. the ſame <hi>S. Aug.</hi> expoundeth <hi>of praying to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> in his <hi>Annot. upon</hi> Job.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Proteſtants hold XXIX.</hi> That the Angels cannot help us.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.13. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael one of the chief Princes came to help me.</hi> which is further verified <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.7.10. Where the ſelf-ſame <hi>Angel,</hi> with his fellow-<hi>Angels,</hi> ſought a battel with the <hi>Dragon,</hi> and with his <hi>Angels.</hi> Therefore they can help us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:32773:43"/>Ibid. verſ. 21. <hi>And there is none that holdeth with me in theſe things, but</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael <hi>your Prince.</hi> Therefore the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels can help us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 12. from <hi>verſe</hi> 7. <hi>to verſe</hi> 12. <hi>Now I know of a ſurety, that the Lord hath ſent his Angel and hath delivered me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See more <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 91. (we 90) 11, 12. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 27.23. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 104. (we 103.) 4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.22. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.10, 15, 16. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9.</p>
               <p>¶ The ancient Fathers affirm the ſame. <hi>S. Juſttn. Apol.</hi> 2. S. <hi>Amb. lib. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vid. Victor. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ticenſ. l.</hi> 3. <hi>de per ſec. V and.</hi> And S. <hi>Aug. de civit. l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 31. ſaith. <hi>The holy Angels do help us without all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, becauſe with their ſpiritual moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (pure and free) they labour or tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel not.</hi> Again in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 62. he ſaith: <hi>The Angels wait upon us pilgrims, and by the commandments of God, do help us:</hi> the place begins, <hi>Attendunt nos peregrinos.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:32773:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXX.</hi> That no Saint deccaſed, hath afterward appeared to any upon earth.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.3. <hi>And behold there appeared unto them</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Elias <hi>talking with them.</hi> Therefore Saints deecaſed, have afterwards ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to ſome on earth.</p>
               <p>Matth. 27.52. <hi>And the graves were opened, and many bodies of Saints which ſlept, aroſe, and came out of the graves af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his reſurrection, and went into the holy City, and appeared unto many,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>2 Maccab. 15.12. <hi>Onias the High-Prieſt, after he was dead, appeared to Indas Macchabaeus alive.</hi> The like did <hi>Samuel</hi> unto <hi>Saul.</hi> What ſhall we ſay then to thoſe, that will deny a truth ſo clear? For ſome ſuch my ſelf have met withall.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Luke</hi> 16.27, 28. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 11.44. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.15. <hi>and</hi> 22. <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.25. <hi>Mark</hi> 5.42.</p>
               <p>¶ See S. <hi>Bede l.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>hiſt. of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:32773:44"/>England,</hi> and S. <hi>Gregory</hi> in his book of <hi>Morals,</hi> in ſunory places.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXI.</hi> That the Saints deceaſed, know not what paſſeth here on earth.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.29. Where <hi>Abraham</hi> knew that there were <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets Books here on earth, which he himſelf had never ſeen when he was alive, as S. <hi>Aug.</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>lib. de cura pro mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuis, cap.</hi> 24. Therefore the Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, know what paſſeth here on earth.</p>
               <p>John 5.45. <hi>Do not think that I will accuſe you to the Father, there is one that accuſeth you, even</hi> Moſes <hi>in whom ye truſt.</hi> But, how could <hi>Moſes</hi> (dead two thouſand years before) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe thoſe that were then living, if the Saints deceaſed know not what paſſeth here on earth?</p>
               <p>Like unto this, is that <hi>Revelat.</hi> 12.10. <hi>And I heard a loud voice, ſaying in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:32773:44"/>heaven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The accuſer of our brethren is caſt down, which accuſeth them before our God day and night.</hi> Now the devils cannot accuſe men day &amp; night before God, but they muſt firſt know where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: who then will for ſhame deny that to Saints and Angels, which muſt needs be granted to the very devils?</p>
               <p>2 Kings 6.12. (we 4. Kings) <hi>O King</hi> Eliſha, <hi>the Prophet that is in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the King of</hi> Iſrael <hi>the words, that thou ſpeakeſt in thy bedchamber.</hi> Hence I thus argue, if the light of Prophecy could extend it ſelf ſo far, as to make known, ſee, and underſtand things ſo ſecret, yea, even to inward thoughts: who can with reaſon deny, that the light of glory can do the ſame in the ſouls of the bleſſed?</p>
               <p>The like is proved out of many other places of Holy Scripture, as 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 5.26. where the Prophet <hi>Elizeus,</hi> being afar off, ſaw all that paſſed betwixt <hi>Naaman,</hi> and <hi>Gieſi</hi> his ſervant. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was wrapt into the third Heaven, and ſaw that which was not to be
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32773:45"/>told to man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. S. <hi>Stephen</hi> ſaw from earth Chriſt ſitting at the right hand of his Father, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. The rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glutton ſaw from hell to heaven (as Proteſtants confeſſe;) how then ſay they, that the Saints cannot know or ſee from heaven to earth?</p>
               <p>And without ſome reciprocal know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, there could be no communion at all, between the Saints in Heaven, and the ſaithful on earth (the which is an article of our Creed) which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the continual paſſage of ſouls thither, doth convince.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.38. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.30. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.3. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 28.14. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.6.23.</p>
               <p>¶ See <hi>Euſebius ſerm. de Annunt. S. Hier. in epitaph. Paul. S. Maximus ſorm. de S. Agnete.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXII.</hi> That the Saints pray not for us.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.8. <hi>The four and twenty Elders fell down before the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:32773:45"/>Lamb, having every one of them harps and golden vials, full of odours, which are the prayers of Saints.</hi> Lo, how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo many divine and unſearchable myſteries ſet down in holy Writ with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out expoſition, it pleaſed God, that the Apoſtle himſelf ſhold clearly open this point unto us, ſaying, <hi>which</hi> (odours) <hi>are the prayers of Saints,</hi> that ſo our adverſaries may have no excuſe of their errour. Therefore the Saints pray for us.</p>
               <p>2 Machab. 15.14. <hi>Then</hi> Onias <hi>anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered, ſaying, This is a lover of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who prayeth much for the people, and for the holy City, to wir,</hi> Jeremiah <hi>the Prophet of God.</hi> Ancient <hi>Origen hom.</hi> 18. <hi>in Joan.</hi> ſaith, it appeareth that Saints departed from this life, have care of the people, as it is written in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Macchabees,</hi> many years after the death of <hi>Jeremy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jeremiah 15.1. <hi>Though</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Samuel <hi>ſtood before me, yet my minde could not be towards this people.</hi> Hence <hi>S. Hierom.</hi> in his Commentaries, and <hi>S. Greg. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>of his Morals. cap.</hi> 12.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:32773:46"/>do gather, that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their death, both could, and did ſometimes, pray for the ſame people: for otherwiſe it ſhould be abſurd to ſay: <hi>Though</hi> Moſes and Samuel <hi>ſtood before me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Baruch 3, 4. <hi>O Lord almighty, thou God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>hear now the prayers of the dead Iſraelites</hi> (we read, <hi>of the dead of</hi> Iſrael.) And <hi>Theodoret</hi> para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſing upon the Prophet <hi>Baruch,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreteth this place as Catholicks do. Therefore the dead of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> prayed for the living.</p>
               <p>Revel. 2.26.27. <hi>And he that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh and keepeth my works unto the end, to him will I give power over the nations, and he ſhall rule them with a rod of Iron.</hi> Since <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore imparteth his power unto them upon nations, therefore they may with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> pray for thoſe over whom they are thus eſtabliſhed. So S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> expoundeth the ſame; wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon the 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We read alſo in the 16. of S. <hi>Luke.</hi> that the rich Glutton in hell, prayed for
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32773:46"/>his brethren that were on earth. If therefore the Saints in Heaven pray not for us their brethren on earth, then we may ſay, that greater is the charity of the damned, then of the ſaved. But this were too abſurd to ſay. A conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which S. <hi>Aug.</hi> draweth from this very place.</p>
               <p>¶ See S. <hi>Aug. ſer.</hi> 15. <hi>de verbis Apoſt. S. Hilar. in Pſalm.</hi> 129. <hi>S. Damaſcen lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de fide cap.</hi> 16. With many others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIII.</hi> That we ought not to beſeech God to grant our prayers in favour of the Saints, or their merits: nor do we receive any benefit thereby.</head>
               <p>TWo wayes there are of praying by the mediation of the bleſſed Saints. The one by beſeeching God to grant our deſires in favour of them, and their merits. The other, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly praying them, to intercede, and pray to God for us. Both being impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned by our Reformers, we will prove them out of their own Bible.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:32773:47"/>The proof of the firſt is contrary to the expreſſe words of their own text, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.13. <hi>Remember</hi> Abraham, Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Iſrael thy <hi>ſervants, to whom thou ſwareſt by thine own ſelf, and ſaidſt unto them, I will multiply your ſeed, as the ſtars of heaven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And our Lord repented</hi> (we read, <hi>was pacified</hi>) <hi>of the evil which he thought to do unto his people.</hi> See how plainly <hi>Moſes</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God, by the mediation of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Patriarchs.</hi> A form of prayer ſo pleaſing to him, as having ſaid a little before, that for their ſin <hi>of Idolatry, he would conſume them,</hi> the memory of his holy Servants being but laid before him, he preſently pardoned them. Therefore we may beſeech God to grant us our prayers in favour of them. <hi>Theod. quaeſt.</hi> 67. <hi>in Exod.</hi> writeth, that <hi>Moſes</hi> not thinking himſelf ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to appeaſe God by himſelf; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the interceſſion of the holy <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs.</hi> And the like doth S. <hi>Aug. quaeſt.</hi> 149. <hi>in Exod.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Now therefore, O Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>keep with thy
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:32773:47"/>ſervant</hi> David, <hi>that which thou haſt promiſed him.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. (we 131) <hi>Lord remember</hi> David, <hi>and all his afflictions.</hi> Lo, again the faith of the ancient Church of God, before the coming of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp; how ſervent they were in this devotion, ſtill alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the memories and merits of their Saints deceaſed, thereby to move Gods mercy towards them. So prayed <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 1.9. So prayed <hi>Iſai</hi> 63.17. So prayed <hi>Heſter</hi> 13, 14. So prayed <hi>David</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.18. na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> for his Interceſſours. Who ever heard a Proteſtant to ſay; Lord remember thine own mother, and all her afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> and their perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions: Nay, they deſire the Papiſts to hold them blameleſs for fear (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) leſt they ſhould blaſpheme.</p>
               <p>Exodus 20.5. <hi>I the Lord thy God am a jealous God, viſiting the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the Fathers upon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, unto the third and fourth genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them that hate me, and ſhewing mercy unto thouſands of them that
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:32773:48"/>love me, and keep my commandements.</hi> Here again God threatneth to puniſh the demerits of wicked men, deceaſed, unto the fourth generation of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren alive: and to reward the merits of goodmen deceaſed, unto the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand generation of their children alive. Therefore we at this very day, receive benefits by means of our godly Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors deceaſed a thouſand generations ago. Thus much proof of the firſt point, and to paſs unto the ſecond.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIIII.</hi> That we ought not expreſly to pray them to pray, or intercede to God for us.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.24. <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Abraham, <hi>have mercy on me, and ſend</hi> Lazarus, <hi>that he he may dip the tip of his finger in water, and cool my tongue, for I am tormented in this flame.</hi> Lo, two Saints are here prayed unto, and beſought in one <hi>ver.</hi> &amp; yet our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:32773:48"/>uſually bid us ſhew them ſo much as one place in all the Bible for proof hereof. Where then, for Gods ſake, are their eyes?</p>
               <p>But they will reply, and ſay, that this is a Parable and not a Prayer: which we deny, offering to be tryed by the voice of ten renowned and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, all affirming this to be a true Hiſtory, and not a Parable, as <hi>Theophylact, Tertullian, Clemens Alex.</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> S. <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> S. <hi>Ambr.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine, S. Gregory, Euthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius,</hi> and our Countreyman <hi>Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bede.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But grant it to be a Parable: what doth this make, either for them, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us? For every Parable is either true in it ſelf, and in the perſons na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or at leaſt is, or may be true in ſome other; or elſe it were a flat lye, or at leaſt a fiction or fable, which I preſume they will never deny.</p>
               <p>Whereupon I thus conclude as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did a little before up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſelf-ſame Hiſtory; If the rich Glutton in Hell, prayed to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:32773:49"/>who</hi> (as our Reformers ſay) was in heaven, why may not we, who are on earth, pray to them who are in heaven.</p>
               <p>Job 5.1. <hi>Call now, if there be any that will anſwer thee, and to which of the Saints wilt thou turn?</hi> (we reade <hi>and turn to ſome of the Saints.</hi>) Now if it had not been the cuſtome in the time of <hi>Iob,</hi> to invocate the holy Saints, it had been frivolous for <hi>Eliphas,</hi> to have asked <hi>Iob,</hi> to which of the Saints he would turn him. Whereto I adde, that S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> expounds this very place in his Annotations upon <hi>Iob,</hi> in the ſame ſenſe that Catholicks do; yea, and long before him the <hi>Seventy Interpreters.</hi> See more 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Heſter</hi> 13.15. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.9. and 15.10.</p>
               <p>¶ The Fathers that affirm the ſame, are, S. <hi>Dionyſius cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Eccleſ. Hier. S. Athanaſius ſerm. de Annun. S. Baſil. orat. in</hi> 44. <hi>Mart. S. Chryſoſt. hom.</hi> 66. <hi>ad popul.</hi> Finally, S. <hi>Hier.</hi> prayed to S. <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, in Epi.</hi> S. <hi>Paula.</hi> S. <hi>Maximus</hi> to S. <hi>Agnes, ſerm. de</hi> S. <hi>Bernard</hi> to our B. Lady and the like.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:32773:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXV.</hi> That the Bones, or Relicks of Saints, are not to be kept, or reſerved, no vertue proceeding from them, after they be once dead.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.13.22. where it is written, that the bones of <hi>Eliſeus,</hi> being touched by one that was dead, did revive him. But this could not be, had not ſome vertue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from them.</p>
               <p>Acts 5.14, 15. <hi>And believers were the more added to the Lord, multitudes both of men and women; inſomuch that they brought forth the ſick into the ſtreets, and laid them on Beds and Couches, that at the leaſt the ſhadow of</hi> Peter <hi>paſſing by, might overſhadow ſome of them.</hi> It followeth in ours <hi>(and that they all might be delivered from their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities)</hi> which is quite, left out in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bibles, though thoſe ſet forth in the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> reign have it as ours, in particular, that of <hi>Anno</hi> 1560. Whereupon S. <hi>Aug.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:32773:50"/>ſer.</hi> 39. <hi>de Sanctis,</hi> ſaith: <hi>If the ſhadow of S.</hi> Peters <hi>body could help them, how much more now the fulneſſe of his power?</hi> Wherein he ſuppoſeth two things. The one; that the ſhadow of his body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here on earth, did both help and heal infirmities (which the late <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Bibles all leave out, as I ſaid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it makes not for them.) The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that being in Heaven, he can ſtill help us by his power.</p>
               <p>Acts 19.11.12. <hi>And God wrought ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial miracles by the hands of</hi> Paul, <hi>ſo that, from his body were brought unto the ſick, hand-kerchiefs, or aprons, and the diſeaſes departed from them, and the evil ſpirits went out of them. S.</hi> Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom. <hi>tom.</hi> 5. <hi>cont. Gentiles, Quod Chriſtus ſit Deus,</hi> in a whole book pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth hereby, and by the like virtue of other Saints, and their Relicks, that Chriſt their Lord and Maſter is God, whoſe ſervants ſhadows, and napkins could do no ſuch wonders.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Exodus</hi> 13.19. 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.8.14. <hi>John</hi> 1.27. Where S. <hi>John</hi> had a reverend eſteem of the very latchet of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:32773:50"/>our Saviours ſhoe, as of a Relick, which he was not worthy to unbuckle, or touch with his hand: And the woman with the bloudy flux, of the hem of his holy garment.</p>
               <p>¶ See the ancient Fathers that affirm the ſame. <hi>Euſeb. l.</hi> 7. <hi>hiſt. cap.</hi> 15. <hi>S. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius, in vita S. Antonii. S. Baſil in Pſal.</hi> 115. <hi>S. Chryſoſt. ſer. de ſanctis Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventio &amp; Maximo.</hi> And S. <hi>Amb.</hi> ſaith, <hi>But if you ask me, what I honour in fleſh diſſolved, I honour in the Martyrs fleſh his wounds, received for Chriſts Name.</hi> And, <hi>I honour his aſhes, made holy by the confeſſion of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Proteſtants hold. XXXVI.</hi> That creatures cannot be ſanctified, or made more holy then they are already of their own nature.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4. <hi>For every creature of God is good, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be refuſed, if it be received with thanks-giving, for it is ſanctified by the word of God, and prayer.</hi> Yea,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:32773:51"/>it was a common uſe in the primitive Church, to bring bread to Prieſts to be hallowed, <hi>Author oper. imp. hom.</hi> 14. <hi>in Matth.</hi> and being bleſſed, to ſend it for ſacred tokens from one Chriſtian to another, as <hi>S. Aug.</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>ep.</hi> 31.34.35.36.</p>
               <p>Mat. 23.17. <hi>Ye fools and blind, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is greater, the gold, or the temple that ſanctifieth the gold?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mat. 23.19. <hi>Ye fools and blind whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is greater, the gift, or the Altar that ſanctifieth the gift?</hi> Lo, how plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our Lord affirmeth in both theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that the <hi>Temple</hi> ſanctifieth the <hi>Gold,</hi> and the <hi>Altar</hi> the <hi>Gift:</hi> and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all creatures, ſevered from common and profane uſe to religion and worſhip of God, are thereby made ſacred and holy. Are not they therefore much to be blamed, who keep ſuch a ſcoffing at Holy water, Holy aſhes, and the like?</p>
               <p>See more 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 2. (we 4.2.) where the Prophet <hi>Eliſeus</hi> applied ſalt to the healing and purifying of the waters. <hi>Toby</hi> 6.8. where the Angel <hi>Raphael</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:32773:51"/>the Liver of a Fiſh, to drive away the Devil. 1 <hi>Samuel</hi> (we 1 Kings) 16. Where <hi>Davids, Harp</hi> and Pſalmody keep the evil ſpirit away from <hi>Saul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶ See S. <hi>Greg. l.</hi> 1. <hi>dial. cap.</hi> 4. <hi>S. Aug. lib.</hi> 18. <hi>de civit. Dei. S. Hier. in the the life of Hilarion, poſt medium S. Bede, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 30. <hi>hiſt. Angliae.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVII.</hi> That children may be ſaved by their Parents faith, without the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of holy Baptiſm.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words, both of truth it ſelf, and alſo of their own Bible, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Verily, verily I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, except a man be born of water, and of the ſpirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> Therefore they cannot be ſaved without Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>Tit. 3.5. <hi>Not by works of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which we have done, but according to his mercy he ſaved us, by the waſhing of regeneration, and renewing of the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Marc. 16.16. <hi>He that believeth, and is baptiſed, ſhall be ſaved: but he that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:32773:52"/>believeth not, ſhall be damned.</hi> Seeing Infants therefore cannot believe, they muſt at the laſt be baptized, or elſe they cannot be ſaved.</p>
               <p>Here they will object againſt us that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. That the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the faithful are ſanctified. But if they underſtand by their <hi>ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that they are born without ſin, they do directly oppugne S. <hi>Paul.</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth (<hi>Eph.</hi> 1.) that we are all born the Sons of wrath. Yea, S. <hi>Paul.</hi> in the ſelf-ſame place ſaith, that the unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Women is ſanctified by the belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Man: and yet I hope they will not ſay, that ſhe obtains thereby the full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of her ſins.</p>
               <p>Gen. 17.14. <hi>The uncircumciſed Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>childe, whoſe fleſh of his fore-skin is not circumciſed, that Soul ſhall be cut off from his people.</hi> But Circumciſion was not more neceſſary to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> than Baptiſm to the Chriſtians; therfore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶ See S. <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de peccat. merit. &amp; remiſs. c.</hi> 30. <hi>ep.</hi> 90.91. <hi>S. Leo. epiſt.</hi> 80. <hi>ad Epiſcop. Campaniae.</hi> S. <hi>Irenaeus. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 19. S. <hi>Cyp. l.</hi> 3. <hi>ep.</hi> 8 <hi>ad Fidum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:32773:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVIII.</hi> That the Sacrament of Confirmation is not neceſſary, nor to be uſed.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.14. <hi>Peter and John prayed for them, that they might receive the Holy Ghoſt (for as yet he was fallen upon none of them, only they were baptized in the Name of the Lord Jeſus.) Then laid they their hands on them, and they received the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Thus the holy Ghoſt is given in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, which was not given in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm: how then is it not neceſſary, nor to be uſed?</p>
               <p>Hebr. 6.1. <hi>Therefore leaving the principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt, let us go on unto perfection, not laying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the foundation of repentance from dead works, and of Faith towards God, of the Doctrine of Baptiſme, and of laying on of hands.</hi> Confirmation is here called one of the <hi>Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:32773:53"/>of repentance:</hi> How then not neceſſary, nor to be uſed?</p>
               <p>¶ See the Fathers that affirm the ſame. <hi>Tertul. lib. de Reſur. carnis.</hi> S. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cianus lib. de Baptiſmo.</hi> S. <hi>Ambr. lib. de Sacram.</hi> S. <hi>Hierom. contra Lucifer.</hi> And laſtly, S. <hi>Cypr. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 1. ſpeaking both of baptiſm and confirmation, ſaith, <hi>That they may be ſanctified, and be the ſons of God, if they be born in both Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIX.</hi> That the bread of the Supper of our Lord, was but a figure, or remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the body of Chriſt received by faith, and not his true, and very body.</head>
               <p>COntrary both to the expreſſe words and truth of their own Bible, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.15. <hi>With deſire I have deſired to eat this paſſeover with you before I ſuffer:</hi> Now to refer theſe words to a figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive eating onely by Faith, were moſt abſurd: for we cannot ſay, that Jeſus Chriſt could receive or eat himſelf in this ſenſe ſith all Divinity forbids
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:32773:53"/>us to admit Faith in the Son of God; Therefore that <hi>Paſche,</hi> which he ſo greatly deſired to eat with his diſciples before he ſuffered. was the <hi>Paſche</hi> of his own true body.</p>
               <p>Luke 22.16. <hi>For I ſay unto you, I will not any more drink of the fruit of the vine, until it be fulfilled in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi> Words of wonderfull force, and which cannot be underſtood figuratively, no more than the former; it being a thing as clear as the Sun, that of material bread and drink, there is no uſe at all above in Heaven.</p>
               <p>John 6.51. <hi>I am the living bread which came down from Heaven: if any man eat of this bread, he ſhall live for ever: And the bread that I will give is my fleſh, which I will give for the life of the world. Beza</hi> is very angry, when we ask him, If the bread that came down from Heaven, be living, or life-giving bread? He willingly grants us the latter, but cannot endure to hear tell of the former, and therefore tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>life-giving,</hi> inſtead of <hi>living.</hi> But this is abſurd, for the Sun is life-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:32773:54"/>but is not living: and being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be living, what elſe is it but his body?</p>
               <p>And note withall, that thus our Lord ſpake of this bleſſed bread, before he gave it.</p>
               <p>Matth. 26.26. <hi>Take, eat, this is my body.</hi> And <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. <hi>This is my body, which is given for you.</hi> What I pray can be ſpoken more plain? Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, they will needs maintain and affirm, that what he gave, and they received, was nothing elſe but bare bread.</p>
               <p>Note alſo, that our Lord ſpake this at the very giving thereof, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. <hi>The cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the bloud of Christ? The bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi> And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. he addeth: <hi>He that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, not diſcerning the Lords body.</hi> Thus both <hi>before</hi> our Lord gave it; <hi>at</hi> the very giving of it, and his Apoſtles and Diſciples <hi>after</hi> he had given it unto
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:32773:54"/>them, and they to others, all of them call it expreſly our <hi>Lords B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, againſt their true and reall receiving of Chriſt by Faith, I ſay: Either the Soul aſcendeth to Heaven, there to feed on Chriſt by faith (which <hi>Calvin</hi> confeſſeth:) or elſe Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendeth to earth to feed the ſame. Not the firſt, for ſo the unglorified Soul of man ſhould be in two places at once; which yet they deny even to the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied body of Jeſus Chriſt. Not the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, for ſo Chriſt ſhould be in two places at once, whom yet they ſay the Heavens muſt contain till the day of Judgement, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>¶ See the ancient Fathers that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the ſame, S. <hi>Ignat. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p. ad Smyr. S. Juſtin Apol.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Antoninum. S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian ſer.</hi> 4. <hi>de lapſis. S. Ambr. l.</hi> 4. <hi>de Sacram.</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is bread before the words of the Sacrament, but after,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of bread it is made the fleſh of Chriſt. S. Remigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſaith, <hi>The fleſh which the Word of God took in the Virgins womb, and the bread conſecrated in the Church, are one Body.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:32773:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XL.</hi> That we ought to receive under both kinds; and that one alone ſufficeth not.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>John</hi> 6.51. <hi>If any man eat of this bread, he ſhall live for ever, and the bread which I will give, is my fleſh.</hi> Here everlaſting life is promiſed by our Lord himſelf, to him that eats of this bread onely: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one kinde doth ſuffice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.30.8.35. Chriſt at <hi>Emaus</hi> communicated to his Diſciples under one kinde. Both S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Theophilact</hi> expound this place of the B. Sacrament in the ſame ſence, <hi>lib. de conſenſ. Evang, cap.</hi> 35. <hi>S. Chryſoſt. hom.</hi> 17. <hi>operis imperfecti. S. Thomas of Aquin,</hi> and many others.</p>
               <p>But they will alleadge to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that of S. John, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs you eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his bloud, you ſhall not have life in you,</hi> The anſwer hereto is very eaſie, which
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:32773:55"/>is, that the conjunction <hi>and,</hi> is there ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken disjunctively inſtead of <hi>or,</hi> as is learnedly obſerved by Doctour <hi>Kelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> in his reply to M. <hi>Sutcliff,</hi> p. 189. Again, Chriſt in thoſe words, teacheth us the precept, and not the manner of the precept; that is to ſay, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to receive his body and his bloud, without determining whether under one kinde, or under both, as the Counſel of <hi>Trent</hi> declareth. For he that ſaid; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs you eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his bloud, you ſhall not have life in you,</hi> hath alſo ſaid, <hi>If any one eat of this bread, he ſhall live for ever.</hi> And he that ſaid, <hi>He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my bloud, hath life everlaſting,</hi> hath alſo ſaid; <hi>The bread which I will give, is my fleſh for the life of the World.</hi> He that ſaid; <hi>Who ſo eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my bloud, dwelleth in me, and I in him,</hi> hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaid; <hi>He that eateth this bread, ſhall live for ever.</hi> Therefore one alone doth ſuffice.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="part">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:32773:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>They further hold. XLI.</hi> That there is not in the Church, a true and proper Sacrifice; and that the Maſs is not a Sacrifice.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible, <hi>Mac.</hi> 1.11. <hi>From the riſing of the ſun even to the going down of the ſame, my Name ſhall be great among the Gentiles, and in every place Incenſe ſhall be offered to my Name, and a pure offering.</hi> But this Sacrifice, or pure Offering cannot be underſtood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> upon the Croſs (as they would have it) which was offered onely once, and in one place, and then alſo not among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> nor yet can be ever iterated: therefore neither is, nor can be other, than the dayly Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. (we 109.) 4. <hi>The Lord hath ſworn, and will not repent, Thou art a Prieſt for ever, after the order of</hi> Melchiſedech. But <hi>Melchiſedechs</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was made in bread and wine:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:32773:56"/>therefore it muſt either be granted, that our <hi>Saviour</hi> doth now ſacrifice (yea, and ever ſhall) in bread and wine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove in Heaven (which were abſurd to ſay:) or elſe that this is meant of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſs, whereon the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of his Prieſt-hood doth depend on earth. Nor can this be in a ſpiritual ſort onely, for that would not make him a Prieſt of any certain order, as <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was.</p>
               <p>Luke 22.19. <hi>This is my body, which is given for you.</hi> Which words do plainly prove, not onely that <hi>Chriſts</hi> body is truly preſent, but withal ſo preſent, as that it is given, offered, and ſacrificed for us. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith not, <hi>which is given to you, broken to you, or ſhed to you,</hi> but, <hi>for you;</hi> Which clearly ſheweth it to be a ſacrifice: it being evident, that one would never ſay of the Sacrament (in the quality of a Sacrament) that it is given for man, but to man; that is to ſay, that a man receiveth it: and contrarywiſe of a Sacrifice, that it is offered, not to man, but for man.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:32773:57"/>See more <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.15, 16, 17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.1.3. <hi>He.</hi> 9.11.</p>
               <p>¶ The Fathers that affirm the ſame, are S. <hi>Clement. Apoſt. cont. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. who called it: <hi>A reaſonable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloudy, and miſtycal Sacrifice.</hi> S. Aug. <hi>A ſingular, or moſt excellent ſacrifice. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cont. adverſ. leg. and Prophet. cap.</hi> 18.19. S. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> hom. in Pſal. 95. <hi>The myſtical table, a pure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloudy hoſt, a heavenly and moſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Sacrifice.</hi> Iſichius in <hi>Levit. cap.</hi> 4. ſaith; <hi>that</hi> Chriſt, <hi>preventing his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, firſt ſacrificed himſelf in his myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſupper, and afterwards on the Croſs.</hi> S. <hi>Greg. Niſſen. orat.</hi> 4. <hi>de Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione,</hi> proving that our <hi>Saviour</hi> gave his body and bloud in ſacrifice for us in his laſt ſupper, ſaith excellently; <hi>That a man cannot eat the ſheep, unleſs the ſlaughter go before;</hi> and yet aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth this to have been done by <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his laſt ſupper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:32773:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XLII.</hi> That Sacramental <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction is not to be uſed to the ſick.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible, <hi>James</hi> 5.14. <hi>Is any ſick among you? Let him call for the Elders of the Church, and let them pray over him, anointing him with oyl in the name of the Lord: and the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of faith ſhall ſave the ſick, and the Lord ſhall raiſe him up, and if he have committed ſins, they ſhall be forgiven him.</hi> Hardly is there any Sacrament whereof the matter, the miniſter, and the effect, are more expreſly ſpecified in all the Scripture, then of this. The form is the prayer, <hi>Let them pray over him.</hi> The matter, the oyl, <hi>Anointing him with oyl.</hi> The Miniſter, a Prieſt, or Elder of the Church, <hi>Let him call for the Elders of the Church.</hi> The primary effect is, the forgiveneſs of ſins, and the ſecondary, the eaſing of the ſick in body, ſaying: <hi>And the Lord ſhall raiſe him up, and if he have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:32773:58"/>ſins, they ſhall be forgiven him.</hi> Therefore Sacramental Unction, is to be uſed to the ſick.</p>
               <p>Mark 6.13. <hi>And they anointed with oyl many that were ſick, and heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them.</hi> Where it is clear, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves, put in practice this holy Unction. Which <hi>Beza</hi> confeſſeth in his Annotations; ſaying, that it was a Symbole of admirable &amp; ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral virtue. And had he not reaſon ſo to ſay? For oyl of it ſelf, could not be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally the Antidote of all diſeaſes: and albeit it were, yet the Apoſtles were not ſent to practiſe Phiſick, but to preach the Goſpel; Yea, it were a thing both ridiculous, and impious to make them Trayclears, Carriers of Drugs, or Paracelſians.</p>
               <p>Mark 16.18. <hi>They ſhall lay hands on the ſick, and they ſhall recover.</hi> But firſt, our Reformers are no true Prieſts. Secondly, they lay not their hands upon the ſick. Thirdly, they anoint them not with oyl in the name of the Lord, as S. <hi>James</hi> willeth. Let them ſay the truth then and ſhame the devil,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:32773:58"/>are not they ſick in their wits, who will oppoſe ſo plain Scriptures?</p>
               <p>¶ See the Fathers that affirm the ſame. <hi>Origen. hom.</hi> 2. <hi>in Levit. S. Chryſoſt. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de ſacerd. S. Aug. in Speculo. &amp; ſerm.</hi> 215. <hi>de temp. Venerable Bede in</hi> 6. <hi>Mark &amp;</hi> 5. <hi>Jac.</hi> with many others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIII.</hi> That no interiour Grace is given by impoſition of hands, in Holy Orders. And that ordinary Vocation, and miſſion of Paſtors, is not neceſſary in the Church.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Neglect not the gift</hi> (we reade <hi>grace</hi>) <hi>that is in thee, which was given thee by propheſie, with the laying on the hands of the Presbytery.</hi> See how plain it is that holy Orders do give place. <hi>D. Kel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſon</hi> handling this Queſtion touching the Miſſion of the Reformers, proveth learnedly (in his Reply <hi>page</hi> 7. &amp; 44.)
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:32773:59"/>that this foundation being diſproved, the whole frame of their Church and Religion falls: yea, that they have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true faith, nor worſhip of God; and his reaſon is this: if faith depend of hearing, hearing of Preaching, Preaching, and adminiſtration of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of Miniſters and Preachers, and Preachers and Miniſters of their miſſion, where there is no miſſion (as they have none) there can be no true faith, nor lawful adminiſtration of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and conſequently no Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Therefore vocation is neceſſary in the Church.</p>
               <p>1 Tim. 1.6. <hi>Wherefore I put thee in remembrance, that thou ſtir up the gift of God which is in thee, by the putting on thy hands.</hi> How plain the Holy Scripture is againſt them. But they reply, that laying on of hands is not needful to them, who have already in them the ſpirit of God, and inward annointing of the holy Ghoſt. To which very queſtion <hi>Theodoret</hi> maketh anſwer, that God commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> (<hi>Num.</hi> 27.) to lay his hands upon <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue,</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:32773:59"/>whereas by the Teſtimony of God himſelf, <hi>Joſue</hi> had already in him the ſpirit of God: S. <hi>Paul,</hi> although he were called immediately from Heaven, yet was afterward ſent with laying on of hands, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.3.</p>
               <p>Heb. 5.4. <hi>And no man taketh this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour unto himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was</hi> Aaron. Here our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries reply again, that <hi>Aaron</hi> had no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal vocation; but this is eaſily ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, for <hi>Aaron</hi> was the firſt of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and therefore could not have his calling by ſucceſſion, and whoſe caſe is far unlike to our Reformers, unleſſe they will confeſſe alſo that they are the firſt of their Order; wherein they ſhall be eaſily believed.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Num.</hi> 27.23.</p>
               <p>¶ See alſo the holy Fathers that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the ſame, S. <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>quaeſt. ſuper. Num. S. Cyp. ep. ad Magnum. Optatus Milevit.</hi> the place begins; <hi>Ne quis Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur. Tertullian in praeſcript.</hi> the place begins, <hi>Edant origines.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="part">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:32773:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIV.</hi> That the Prieſts, and other Religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who have vowed their chastity of God, may freely marry, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their vow.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.22. <hi>When thou ſhalt vow a vow unto the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt not ſlack to pay it; for the Lord thy God will ſurely require it of thee, and it would be ſin in thee: but if thou ſhalt forbear to vow, it ſhall be no ſin in thee.</hi> Out of which words, two things are clearly proved; The one, that it is both lawfull and laudable to make Vows; the other, that Vows being once made, do binde, where o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe there was no obligation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, therefore ſuch as have vowed Chaſtity, may not, nor ought not after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, attempt to marry; which if they do, they break their Vow.</p>
               <p>1 Tim. 5.11, 12. <hi>But the younger widdows refuſe, for when they have begun to wax wanton againſt Christ, they will marry, having damnation, becauſe they have caſt off their firſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:32773:60"/>faith.</hi> All the ancient Fathers that write upon this place, expound theſe words of the Apoſtle, of the Vow of Chaſtity, or of the faith and promiſe made to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to live continently; as is abundantly proved in the Rhemes Teſtament upon this place.</p>
               <p>1 Tim. 5.15. <hi>For ſome already turned aſide after Satan,</hi> To marry, after the vow of chaſtity once made, is here termed by the Apoſtle himſelf, <hi>turning aſide after Sathan.</hi> And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it is, that we call the Religious that after marry (as <hi>Luther, Bucer, Peter Martyr,</hi> and the reſt of that laſcivious rabble) Apoſtates, Gods a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, inceſtuous, ſacrilegious and the like.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.16. <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.2.18. <hi>Joſue</hi> 21.26. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 35.18. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 21.23.</p>
               <p>¶ See alſo the Fathers in confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof. <hi>S. Aug. lib. de bono viduit. c.</hi> 9. <hi>Athanaſius lib. de virginitat. S. Epiphanius haereſ.</hi> 48. <hi>S. Hier. cont. Jov. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>What is to break their firſt faith</hi> (ſaith <hi>S.</hi> Aug?) <hi>They vowed and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:32773:61"/>performed not,</hi> in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 75. The place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins; <hi>Quid eſt, primam fidem,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLV.</hi> That faſting, and abſtinence from cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain meats is not grounded on holy Scripture, nor cauſeth any ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual good.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 35.5. <hi>And I ſet before the Sons of the houſe of the</hi> Rechabites, <hi>pots full of Wine, and Wine-cups, and I ſaid unto them, drink ye Wine. But they ſaid, we will drink no Wine, for</hi> Jonadab <hi>the Son of</hi> Rechab, <hi>our Father, commanded us, ſaying; Ye ſhall drink no Wine, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye, nor your ſons for ever. Thus have we obeyed</hi> Jonadab <hi>our Father, in all that he hath charged us.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faſting is grounded upon holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>Luk. 1.15. <hi>For he ſhall be great in the ſight of the Lord, and ſhall drink neither Wine nor ſtrong drink.</hi> Thus was abſtinence, not onely foretold, but alſo preſcribed by the Angel; which plainly proveth that it was both a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:32773:61"/>thing, and alſo an act of religion in S. <hi>John Bapt.</hi> as it was in the <hi>Nazarites</hi> and <hi>Rechabites</hi> afore-mentioned.</p>
               <p>Acts 13.3. <hi>And when they had fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they ſent them away.</hi> Hence the Church of God hath ſufficient ground and warrant for the uſing and preſcribing of publick faſts (which was not faſting from ſin, as our Reformers (forſooth) pretend, for ſuch faſting they were ever bound to keep) and that at ſuch times, or ſeaſons as the Church pleaſed to preſcribe (as in Lent, or the like) and not when every man liſts, or the toy takes him in the head, as <hi>Arius</hi> and other Hereticks did teach, teſtified by S. <hi>Aug. Haereſ</hi> 53.</p>
               <p>Matt. 17.21. <hi>Howbeit, this kinde of devils, goeth not out, but by prayer and faſting.</hi> Behold the great force of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and faſting, able to expell the very devil. Therefore it cauſeth great ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual good.</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Joel</hi> 2.12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.15.29. <hi>Toby</hi> 12.8. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.37. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.22. 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11.37.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:32773:62"/>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Num.</hi> 30.14.1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.</p>
               <p>¶ And the Fathers. <hi>S. Ignat. ad Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip. S. Baſil orat. de jejunio. S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. orat. in ſanct. Lavacrum. &amp; hom.</hi> 1. <hi>in Gen. S. Ambr. ſer.</hi> 4. <hi>S Hier. in cap.</hi> 18. <hi>Iſa.</hi> and many others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLVI.</hi> That Jeſus Chriſt deſcended not into hell, nor delivered thence the ſouls of the Fathers.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſs words of their own Bible, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. <hi>When he aſcended up on high, he led Captivity captive</hi> (in their margent, <hi>or a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of captives</hi>) <hi>and gave gifts unto men. Now that he aſcended, what is it, but that he alſo deſcended firſt into the lower parts of the earth?</hi> Theſe freed Captives to be the ſouls of the glorified, no man in his right wits will ſay; nor the ſouls of the damned, for ſo the devils ſhould be brought again into heaven; therefore they were the ſouls of the Fathers which Chriſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered out of <hi>Limbus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Acts 20.27. <hi>Becauſe thou wilt not leave my ſoul in hell, neither wilt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:32773:62"/>thou ſuffer thine holy one to ſee corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Theſe very words S. <hi>Aug.</hi> appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the proof of a third place, and ſaith: <hi>Who but an infidell, will deny</hi> Chriſt <hi>to have deſcended into hell? Epiſt.</hi> 99. <hi>ad Exod.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 Pet. 3.18.19. <hi>Being put to death in the fleſh, but quickned by the ſpirit, by which alſo he went, and preached unto the ſpirits in priſon.</hi> Now to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by the word <hi>priſon,</hi> heaven there is no ſenſe, ſince it is called the ſeat of God, and not the priſon of God. To underſtand it of the wicked, <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf oppoſeth this opinion, and maintains that S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of the good, who were known from the dayes of <hi>Noah.</hi> And hereto, that this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine deſtroieth an article of our Creed Therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> deſcended into hell.</p>
               <p>Heb. 11.38.39.40. <hi>And thoſe all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obtained a good report, through faith received not the promiſe:</hi> (to wit of heaven) <hi>God having provided ſome better thing for us, that they without us ſhould not be made perfect:</hi> to wit, in their perfect and compleat glory.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:32773:63"/>Whence it follows neceſſary that they muſt needs grant another place, diſtinct as well from the Heaven of the ſaved, as from the Hell of the damned, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe holy ſouls were detained.</p>
               <p>Mat. 12.40. <hi>For as</hi> Jonas <hi>was three days and three nights in the Whales belly, ſo ſhall the Son of man be three days and three nights, in the heart of the earth.</hi> But how I pray, is this Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure fulfilled, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> were not as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny days and nights in the heart of the earth, as <hi>Jonas</hi> was, who was not in the whales belly in body only, but alſo in ſoul? Whence it followeth, that either <hi>Chriſts</hi> holy ſoul, was three days, and three nights in the heart of the earth, as well as his body, or that this place of Scripture, is either falſe, or unfulfilled. Which were moſt abſurd to affirm.</p>
               <p>Matth. 27.52.53. <hi>And the graves were opened, and many bodies of Saints which ſlept, aroſe, and came out of the graves after his reſurrection, and went into the holy City, and appeared unto many.</hi> Underſtood by <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> of <hi>Limbus Patrum,</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:32773:63"/>writing to the Citizens of <hi>Trallis</hi> thus: <hi>many aroſe with our Lord, for the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſaith, that many of the bodies that ſlep aroſe with our Lord. He deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alone, returned with a multitude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Zach. 9.11. <hi>As for thee alſo by the bloud of thy Covenant, I have ſent</hi> (we read <hi>let</hi>) <hi>forth thy priſoners, out of the pit, wherein is no water.</hi> Both <hi>S. Hier,</hi> and <hi>S. Cyril,</hi> underſtand this pit, to be meant of <hi>Limbus Patrum.</hi> And with very great reaſon, for how abſurd were it to ſay, that the damned have their ſhare <hi>in the bloud of the Covenant?</hi> Or that they are <hi>ſet forth</hi> of their infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal pit? Or that they may be ſaid to be <hi>thy priſoners</hi> (that is <hi>Chriſt</hi>) but rather the priſoners of the devils? Yea, where I pray (to ſpeak properly) hath <hi>Chriſt</hi> had any priſoners at all (which he hath let forth) if not out of this place? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, either <hi>Chriſt</hi> let forth priſoners out of <hi>Limbus Patrum,</hi> or this place likewiſe as the former, is either falſe, or not yet fulfilled.</p>
               <p>Like unto this, is that of 1. <hi>Samuel</hi> 2.6. <hi>The Lord killeth, and maketh
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:32773:64"/>alive, he bringeth down to the grave</hi> (we read, <hi>hell</hi>) <hi>and bringeth up</hi> (we read <hi>back again.</hi>) See how plain and conform the faith of that old Church was, and is to this of ours, <hi>bringeth down to hell or bring-back again,</hi> which hardly in any clear ſenſe can be aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if <hi>Limbus Patrum</hi> be denied. As for the word <hi>(grave)</hi> which they erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neouſly have added in ſtead of <hi>Hell,</hi> to diminiſh the force of ſo plain a place; why do they not as well foiſt the ſame into their Creed, in ſtead of <hi>Hell,</hi> as here they have done, and ſay, <hi>Was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, dead an buried, he deſcended into the grave?</hi> Who doth not ſee this abſurdity?</p>
               <p>See more <hi>Oſee</hi> 6.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.10. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3 19. <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 24 45. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.7. <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.35.</p>
               <p>¶ See alſo the Fathers that affirms the ſame. <hi>S. Hier. in</hi> 4. <hi>and Epheſ. S. Greg. lib.</hi> 13. <hi>Moral. cap.</hi> 20. <hi>S. Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. The place begins: <hi>Futurum eſt enim,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="part">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:32773:64"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XLVII.</hi> That there is no Purgatory fire, or other priſon, wherein ſins may be ſatisfied for after this life.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13.25. <hi>The fire ſhall try every mans work; of what ſort it is. If any mans work ſhall be burnt, he ſhall ſuffer loſs, but he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhall be ſaved, yet ſo, as by fire.</hi> S. Auguſtine writing upon the 37. <hi>Pſal.</hi> and drawing theſe very words of the Apoſtle into his diſcourſe ſaith: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſaid (he himſelf ſhall be ſafe) that fire is therefore condemned. Yea verily, though ſafe by fire, yet that fire ſhall be more grievous than whotſoever a man can ſuffer in his life.</hi> Thus he. Therefore there is a Purgatory fire, wherein ſins may be ſatisfied for after this life.</p>
               <p>John 11.22. <hi>But I know, that even now, whatſoever thou wilt ask of God, God will give it thee. S. Martha,</hi> the ſiſter of <hi>S. Ma. Magdalen</hi> believed, that our Lord (whom then, ſhe held only for a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:32773:65"/>holy man, or Prophet, and not for the Son of God, could obtain of God, ſomething profitable to her brother <hi>Lazarus,</hi> who was deceaſed. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſaid: <hi>Lord if thou hadſt been here, my brother had not been dead,</hi> ſhe preſently added: <hi>But I know that even now whatſoever thou wilt ask of God, God will give it thee.</hi> Which ſpeech ſhe could never have uſed in any good ſenſe, if ſhe had not learned this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Synagogue, who offered ſacrifices, alms and prayers for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and unleſs ſhe had known and believed, that the dead might be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen by the piety of the living; as <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Allen</hi> learnedly concludeth in his Treatiſe of Purgatory.</p>
               <p>Acts 2.14. <hi>Whom God hath raiſed up loſing the ſorrows of hell.</hi> In which words two things are to be noted, which clearly make for the proof of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The one, that in this place, where <hi>Chriſt</hi> was, there were certain ſorrows and pains. The other, that ſome there were inflicted for ſin, upon whom he beſtowed that gracious benefit as to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:32773:65"/>diſcharge and free them of thoſe pains. For as the Rhemes teſtament very well notes, Chriſt was not in pains himſelf, but loſed other men out of their pains.</p>
               <p>1 Cor. 15.29. <hi>Otherwiſe what ſhall they do, that are baptized for the dead?</hi> From this place an evident proof is drawn touching the help which the ſouls departed out of this world may receive by the Church on earth, and conſequently proveth Purgatory; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the pains and afflictions, which voluntarily we do inflict upon our ſelves, to exempt thoſe that are therein: for to baptize, ſignifieth to afflict ones ſelf, to do pennance, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as is evident in S. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.30. <hi>But I have a baptiſm to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with, and Mark</hi> 10.38.</p>
               <p>Luke 16.9. <hi>And I ſay unto you, make to your ſelves friends of the Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of unrighteouſneſſe, that when ye fail, they may receive you into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting habitation:</hi> S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> upon this place, and S. <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 21. <hi>de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Dei, cap.</hi> 27. ſay, that it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuccour after death, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:32773:66"/>as the word <hi>(fail)</hi> enforceth.</p>
               <p>Luke 23.42. <hi>Lord, remember me when thou comeſt into thy kingdome.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ſaith in his fifth Book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Julian</hi> about the middeſt) that the good Thief in this prayer, preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that (according to the common opinion) ſouls might be holpen after death.</p>
               <p>2 Mac. 12.44, 45. <hi>For if he had not hoped, that they that were ſlain ſhould have riſen again, it had been ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and vain to pray for the dead.</hi> And in the next verſe he concludeth, <hi>That it was an holy and good thought, &amp;c.</hi> This place of holy Scripture, is moſt clear for prayer for the dead: for had it not been the continual doctrine and practiſe of the Church to pray for the dead, neither could <hi>Judas Macchabaeus</hi> (who was himſelf a Prieſt) have ever thought of any ſuch remedy, as to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther twelve thouſand drachms of ſilver to ſend to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> to have pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers made for the relief of the ſouls ſlain in the wars: neither would the multitude of people have either contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:32773:66"/>or the Prieſts of the Temple, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſame, and they thought (as theſe men do) that it had been ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition to pray for the departed, or, that there had been no other place than the hell of the damned, or the heaven of the ſaved.</p>
               <p>See more 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18. 1. <hi>John</hi> 5.16. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Micheas</hi> 7.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.12. <hi>Toby</hi> 4.18. <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.11.</p>
               <p>¶ As alſo the Fathers that affirm the ſame. <hi>S. Ambr. upon the</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. &amp; <hi>ſerm.</hi> 20. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 118. <hi>S. Hier. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>adverſ. Jovin S. Greg. li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 4. <hi>Dialog. cap.</hi> 39. <hi>Origen. hom.</hi> 6. <hi>in cap.</hi> 15. <hi>Exod.</hi> with many others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLVIII.</hi> That it is not lawfull to make, or have Images.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.18. <hi>And thou ſhalt make two Cherubims of God, of beaten work ſhalt thou
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:32773:67"/>make them, in the two ends of the Mercy ſeat.</hi> Theſe graven Angels were Images of the higheſt order of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels (one excepted) which is in heaven, and were made with faces of beautifull young men, and commanded to be ſet up by God himſelf in the Holy of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; which S. <hi>Hierom</hi> witneſſeth the Jews to have worſhipped, <hi>epiſt. ad Marcellam.</hi> Therefore it is lawfull to make Images.</p>
               <p>1 Kings 6.35. <hi>And he carved thereon Cherubims; and Palm-ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, and open Flowers, and covered them with gold, fitted upon the carved work.</hi> Hence is to be gathered, that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of not making <hi>graven Idols,</hi> doth nothing at all concern <hi>Images,</hi> that is to ſay, the true repreſentation of things mecrly imaginary and not ſubſiſting, for as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. <hi>An Idol is nothing.</hi> So that the Idol repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that which is not, the Image that which is; a moſt remarkable difference.</p>
               <p>Again, ſeeing an Idol is that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, which being nothing (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) is repreſented to be ſomething,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:32773:67"/>or that which repreſents the thing that is not; if our Reformers believe the images of Chriſt crucified to be an idol, they then believe that Chriſt was never crucified; for it would follow neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, that the image of Chriſt crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being an idol, therefore Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was never crucified.</p>
               <p>Heb. 9 1.5. <hi>Then verily, the firſt Covenant had alſo ordinances of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſervice, and a worldly ſanctuary,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and over it, the Cherubi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns of glorie, ſhadowing the Mercy-ſeat.</hi> Here S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the images of the <hi>Cherubims,</hi> which <hi>Solomon</hi> made, an <hi>ordinance of divine ſervice,</hi> which our Reformers call the making of idols; whom ſhall we ſooner believe, Bleſſed S. <hi>Paul,</hi> or a Reformed brother?</p>
               <p>To conclude, an image is of ſuch Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and natural right, that all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, imagination, and ſenſe, as well interiour, as exteriour is made by way of images, called <hi>ſpecies ſenſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les,</hi> &amp; <hi>inſenſibiles.</hi> The body cannot be in light, without its ſhadow: the Moon and the Stars imprint their image in the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:32773:68"/>water: a man cannot look in a glaſſe without making his Image, Therefore either God and nature it ſelf doth breake this Commandement as well as we, or elſe it is abſurd to ſay, that we break it in making of Images.</p>
               <p>See more, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.36.42.44. <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.20. <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.2. <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.30. where painting and engraving of Images, is ſo far from being counted Idolatry, that it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be a ſcience Divinely inſuſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Bezaleel</hi> by God himſelf; and ſo the invention of good Images came firſt from God.</p>
               <p>¶ The Fathers that affirm the ſame are <hi>Tert. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de pudicitia, S. Greg. Naz. ep.</hi> 49. <hi>ad Olymp. S. Baſil. orat. in S. Barlaam. S. Aug. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſ avang. cap.</hi> 10. witneſſeth, that in his time Chriſt was to be ſeen pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in many places, between S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="part">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:32773:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIX.</hi> That it is not lawfull to reverence Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, nor to give any honour, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible things.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.5. <hi>And he ſaid, Draw not nigh hither, put off thy ſhooes from off thy feet, for the place whereon thou ſtandeſt, is holy ground.</hi> How clear a place is here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced againſt our Reformers, wherein an inſenſible Creature was commanded by God himſelf to be honoured: for the refraining to tread upon it, was the doing of honour to it. Therefore all dead Images, repreſenting unto us a holy thing may be honoured.</p>
               <p>Pſal. 99.5. <hi>Adore ye the footſtool of his feet.</hi> Which place is ſpoken literally of the Ark of the Teſtament, according to that of 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.2. <hi>I had in my heart to build a houſe of the reſt for the Ark of the Covenant of the Lord, and for the foot-ſtool of our God.</hi> Now the principal reaſon; why the Ark
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:32773:69"/>was worſhipped, was in regard of the images that were ſet upon it, which the <hi>Jews</hi> did worſhip, as S. <hi>Hierom</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth in his Epiſtle <hi>ad Marcellam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Philip. 2.20. <hi>That at the Name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, every knee ſhould bow, of things in Heaven, &amp; things in earth, and things under the earth.</hi> Now, that is <hi>the Name of Jeſus,</hi> which either is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by anothers mouth, printed in a book, or painted and engraven in an image: but at any of theſe we are commanded to bow the knee.</p>
               <p>Again, if images ought not to be worſhipped, we may not (whatſoever the Apoſtle ſaith) bow our knee at the <hi>Name of Jeſus;</hi> ſeeing words, (as <hi>Ariſtoile</hi> ſaith, and as the truth is) are ſigns repreſentative of the things they ſignifie, and are the images of the ears, as the others are of the eyes.</p>
               <p>Num. 21.8. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto Moſes: Make thee a fiery Serpent, and ſet it up upon a pole: and it ſhall come to paſſe that every one that is bit, when he looketh upon it, ſhall live.</hi> Hence are evidently proved di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:32773:69"/>things againſt our Reformers. 1. That God commanded the making of this image. 2. The ſetting of it up for a ſign. 3. He promiſed that the lookers thereon ſhould aſſuredly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuccour and help. 4. He warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the making, the ſetting up, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, and the reverencing thereof to be exempted from breach of the firſt Commandment, by working ſo many, and ſo manifeſt miracles, at and before the preſence thereof. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an image may be made, may be ſet up, may be looked on, and reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as <hi>Doctour Saunders</hi> moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly concludeth, in his <hi>Treatiſe of Images.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶ See Fathers that affirm the ſame. <hi>S. Amb. ſerm.</hi> 1. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 18. <hi>S. Aug. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Trinit. S. Greg. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 5 <hi>ad Joan.</hi> Finally. <hi>S. Baſil</hi> ſaith (<hi>in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian. citat. in</hi> 7. <hi>Sinod.</hi>) <hi>I honour the Hiſtories of Images, and do publickly worſhip them, for this being delivered us from the holy Apoſtles, is not to be forbidden. S. Chryſoſtom</hi> in his Maſs, turned into Latin by <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> ſaith:
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:32773:70"/>
                  <hi>The Prieſt boweth his head to the Image of Chriſt. S. Damaſcen. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. ſaith: <hi>The worſhipping of the Croſs, and of Images, is a Tradition of the Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But before I conclude this point, I deſire to ſolve a few objections, which uſually our Reformers bring againſt the Honour of holy Images.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> 1. <hi>Objection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is taken out of 2 <hi>Kings</hi> (we 4.) 18. where King <hi>Ezechias</hi> broke down the braſen Serpent (whereof we laſt made mention) ſeeing it to be the cauſe of Idolatry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This indeed is a common place, from whence our Adverſaries collect ſundry falſe and ſophiſtical arguments, to wit, from the abuſe of any good thing, to deſtroy it utterly, together with the right uſe thereof. But by the ſame Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, they may as well collect, that the Sun and the Moon ſhould be taken out of the Firmament, becauſe they were worſhipped by the Gentiles for Gods.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:32773:70"/>Likewiſe that the holy Bible ſhould be burnt, becauſe many a one draweth damnable Hereſies forth of the ſame, to his own perdition. Yea, this ſilly Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment borrowed from the abuſe of things, ſerves very fitly to prove the quite contrary, thus: Images have been ſometimes abuſed, therefore they were good in themſelves: for thoſe things which are evil by abuſe onely, muſt needs be good, being well uſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Their</hi> 2. <hi>Objection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You give that honour to Images, which is due to God alone; worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, adoring, and creeping to them, as to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſay the contrary, which thus we prove. The difference of honour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth principally from the minde, and not from the exterior bowing, or demeanour of the body: For if I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate my ſelfe before an Image, or kiſs the ſame, well knowing the while, that it is no God, nor reaſonable Creature, but onely a remembrance of God, towards whom I deſire
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:32773:71"/>to ſhew mine affection; God knoweth how far off mine honour is, from that honour which is due to him alone. As contrariwiſe, If I lay proſtrate at Chriſts feet indeed, kiſſed them, knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my breaſt, held up my hands unto him, called him the Son of God; yet all this while, think him not to be ſo in my heart, mine honour truly ſhould be no honour at all, but a very contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and affront unto Chriſt. Adde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that the words which betoken ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, adoration, worſhip, and the like, are in a manner confounded in all lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages: but the heart from whence the honour proceedeth, knoweth well the difference of every thing. D. <hi>Saunders de Imag. pag.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Their</hi> 3. <hi>Objection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is expreſly forbidden by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to fall down before any Image, or to worſhip it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some of our Reformers themſelves do honour the Sacrament of Chriſts
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:32773:71"/>Supper, which they teach to be an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, or repreſentation of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud. And ſeeing they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve no other ſubſtance to be in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, beſides bread and wine, nor will give the honour of <hi>latria</hi> (as we call it) thereunto; it follows invincibly that they do worſhip, or honour ſome Image. Now, as they would not for all this have us to judge, or call them I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters: even ſo, let it pleaſe them (for their own ſakes) to ſpare us. For as they do not place, or ſtay this honour in the bread and wine, but from thence refer it to Chriſt himſelf: ſo do we transfer all our honour from all I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, unto the firſt form, or pattern, nor ſuffering the ſame to reſt, or end in the Image which we honour. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. ibid. pag.</hi> 52.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Their</hi> 4. <hi>Objection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Image is a Creature, and no God; and to ſet up a Creature to be worſhipped, or adored is flat Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:32773:72"/>Images are ſet up in Churches, not ſpecially to the intent that the people ſhould worſhip, or adore them, but partly to ſtir up our minds to follow the example of thoſe holy men, whoſe Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges we do there behold. So that the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and reverence which is there given to Images, is given as it were by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, &amp; rather, becauſe it may be lawfully given, than becauſe it is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally ſought to be given. As for the Idolatry, which is objected, we are to underſtand, that the word is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of <hi>Latria,</hi> and <hi>Idolum,</hi> and is as much to ſay, as the giving of <hi>Latria,</hi> or of Gods honour unto an <hi>Idol.</hi> But our Images are no Idols, nor the honour we give unto them, that of <hi>Latria;</hi> how then can it be ſaid that Images are ſet up to be uſed to Idolatry?</p>
               <p>Beſides, for further eviction of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, that ſhould charge me with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, for reverencing a Picture, or Image, I would before his face break a <hi>Crucifix,</hi> or tear a <hi>Picture</hi> of any Saint in pieces, and throw the pieces into the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:32773:72"/>fire, and this not out of any contempt, or ſcorn of what the Crucifix, or Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture repreſents, but to ſatisfie him, that I gave them onely an inferiour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative kind of honour, and uſed them as helps to my memory. And then would ſhew him the Councel of <hi>Trent. Seſſion</hi> 25. in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Images are not to be venerated for any virtue, or Divinity is believed to be in them, or for any thing that is to be Petitioned of them, or for any truſt, or confidence, that is to be put in them, as the Gentiles did of old, who repoſed their hope and truſt in their Idols, but becauſe the honour that is exhibited to them, is referred to the Prototypes repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by them,</hi> &amp;c. Thus for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. And who can be ſo ignorant, or malicious, as to ſay this is Idolatry?</p>
               <p>¶ Thus much have I thought good to add in this place, for the inſtruction of the ignorant and unlearned people, who uſe to ſtumble at the doctrine <hi>of the worſhip of Images,</hi> becauſe indeed they underſtand it not. And what is ſaid for the worſhip of them, may
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:32773:73"/>alſo ſerve for the lawfulneſs of making them, ſince the one ſuppoſeth the proof of the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>L.</hi> That no man hath ſeen God in any form, and that therefore his Picture, or I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage cannot be made.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.8. where God appeared unto Adam, <hi>walking in the garden of Paradiſe,</hi> in a corporal form. And <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.12.13. to <hi>Jacob, ſtanding above the ladder,</hi> whereon the Angels aſcended, and deſcended. For we muſt know, that it is onely the outward ſhape and form of the thing, which is expreſſed, either in this, or the like Image, and not the inward ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof, which is not poſſible for any Painter, or Carver to expreſſe; which though it expreſſe not all that is therein, yet that which it expreſſeth is a truth: and thus may God be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to us. Yea, why may not God be expreſſed by Picture, or Image in the ſame form and manner, wherein he hath manifeſted himſelf to mortal eyes?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:32773:73"/>
                  <hi>Ezod.</hi> 32.11. God appeared, and ſpake unto Moſes <hi>face to face,</hi> as one man ſpeaketh to another. To the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.1.5. <hi>Sitting upon a Throne.</hi> To <hi>Daniel</hi> 7.9. <hi>Sitting, wearing gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and having <hi>hair on his head like pure wool.</hi> How then can any wiſe man, doubt, but that, that thing may be lawfully ſet forth, or expreſſed in an outward Image, which neceſſarily muſt be conceived by an inward?</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Kings</hi> (we 3.) 22.19. <hi>I ſaw the Lord ſitting on his Throne, and all the Hoſt of Heaven, ſtanding by him on his right hand; and on his left.</hi> But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they will ſay, that God commands us to hear his word, and the Hiſtories which ſpake of his apparitions, but not to paint them. I anſwer, That ſeeing we learn by our eyes, as well as by our eares, there is no reaſon, why that may not be painted before our eyes, which may be preached to our ears. Again, ſeeing we may finde the aforeſaid Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Hiſtories in the Bible; why may we not as wel ſee them painted in pictures, as written in a Book of white paper?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="part">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:32773:74"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LI.</hi> That bleſſing, or ſigning with the ſign of the Croſſe, is not founded on holy Scripture.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Revelation</hi> 7.3. Where one Angel ſaid to four other Angels: <hi>Hurt not the earth, neither the Sea, nor the Trees, till we have ſealed</hi> (we read. <hi>ſigned</hi>) <hi>the ſervants of our God in their foreheads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.16. <hi>And he took them up in his arms, put his hands upon them, and bleſſed them.</hi> Therefore ſigning and bleſſing is founded in holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>Luke 24.50. <hi>And he led them out as far as to Bethany, and he lift up his hands, and bleſſed them.</hi> Therefore, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>¶ See the Fathers that affirm the ſame, <hi>Dionyſ. Areopagita, cap.</hi> 4.5.6. <hi>Eccleſ. Hier. Tertul. lib. de corona mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. Origen. in Exod. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>hom</hi> 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>S. Cyril. Cat.</hi> 1. <hi>S. Baſil. lib. de ſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanct. cap.</hi> 38. <hi>S. Chryſoſt. bom.</hi> 55. <hi>in Mat. cap.</hi> 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="part">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:32773:74"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LII.</hi> That the publick ſervice of the Church ought not to be ſaid, but in a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage that all the people may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaend.</head>
               <p>COntrary to the expreſſe words of their own Bible, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.8. <hi>And it came to paſs, that while he executed the Prieſts Office before God, in the order of his courſe according to the cuſtome of the Prieſts Office, his lot was to burn Incenſe in the Temple of the Lord; and the whole multitude of people were praying without at the time of Incenſe.</hi> Where it is to be noted. 1.
<list>
                     <item>1. That this was then the common cuſtom.</item>
                     <item>2. All the people were without, and the Prieſt within; how then did they underſtand him?</item>
                  </list> Therefore the publick ſervice of the Church may be ſo ſaid, as all the people underſtand it not.</p>
               <p>Levit. 16.17. <hi>And there ſhall be no man in the Tabernacle of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, when he goeth in to make an attonement in the holy place, untill he come out, and have made an attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for himſelf, and for his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:32773:75"/>and for all the Congregation of Iſrael.</hi> Therefore <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not need to produce the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of Fathers for this point, when the practice of the whole Chriſtian world, for theſe many hundred years together hath been directly contrary to our Reformers herein, againſt which to diſpute (as S. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith) were inſolent madneſs. See the <hi>Rhe. Teſt.</hi> 463. But againſt this they will object out of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture this their probableſt place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.16. <hi>When thou ſhalt bleſs with the ſpirit, how ſhall be that occupieth the room of the unlearned, ſay Amen at thy giving of thanks, ſeeing he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth not what thou ſayeſt? For thou verily giveſt thanks, but the other is not edified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereto I anſwer, that there be two kinds of prayer, or giving of thanks in the Church. The one <hi>Private,</hi> which every man ſayes by himſelf alone. The other <hi>Publick,</hi> which the Prieſt ſaith, in the name and perſon of the whole Church. As concerning <hi>private</hi> prayer, no Catholick denies, but it is very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:32773:75"/>that every man pray in his own tongue, to the end he may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what he ſayes. But for the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> prayers of the Church, it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the common people under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, becauſe it is not they who pray, but the Prieſt in the name of the whole Church For as it was enough for the people of the old Law to know and underſtand, that in ſuch a Sacrifice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted the worſhip of God, although they had not ſo clear an underſtanding of every thing that was done therein (as hath been ſaid:) even ſo in the new Law, when the people aſſiſt at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſſe, acknowledging thereby that God is worſhipped &amp; that it is inſtituted for the rememb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rance of Chriſts death and paſſion, although they underſtand not the Latine tongue, yet are they not diſtitute of the utility and fruit thereof; beſides rhe help of the pious ceremonies therein, which do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in the whole.</p>
               <p>And indeed this place by them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged ſerveth nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but rather againſt them, ſeeing it
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:32773:76"/>proves, that the common ſervice of the Church, was not then in a tongue which every man underſtood, but in another language, which was not ſo common unto all. For S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaying, <hi>How ſhall he that occupieth the room of the unlearned, ſay Amen, at the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of thanks, ſeeing he underſtandeth not what thou ſayeſt,</hi> ſhews that ſuch giving of thanks, was not accuſtomed to be made in the vulgar tongue; and requires, or rather ſuppoſes that in the ſervice of the Church, there ſhould be ſome other to ſupply the place of the unlearned, that is, one that ſhould have further underſtanding of that tongue, in which the ſervice of the Church is ſaid. But had the ſervice been in the vulgar tongue, there needed no man to have ſupplied the place of the Idiot, that underſtandeth not So that, S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhews moſt clearly, that ſuch ſervice was not exerciſed in a vulgar tongue, but in another which was not common to the whole people (ſuch as the Latin tongue is now in <hi>England,</hi> as alſo throughout the whole Eaſt) and yet was not in the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:32773:76"/>contrary extream, that is to ſay, wholy ſtrange, or utterly barbarous.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing our Adverſaries have this place continually in their mouths, and thereby deceive the ſimple people, I would have them to know that this Text of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> is greatly perverted by the Reformers themſelves. For whereas the Greek and Latin Text hath, <hi>He who ſupplies the place of an Idiot, how ſhall he ſay Amen?</hi> the Miniſters of <hi>Geneva,</hi> in many of their Bibles, have turned the ſame moſt deceitfully and maliciouſly, thus: <hi>He that is an Idiot, how ſhall he ſay Amen?</hi> As if there were no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt an Idiot, and he who ſupplies the place of an Idiot?</p>
               <p>Moreover, the thankſ-giving to which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>Amen</hi> ſhould be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is not at all practiſed in many of our Reformed Churches, where neither Idiots, nor thoſe that ſupply the place of Idiots, do anſwer <hi>Amen,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> willeth; ſeeing they have altered <hi>Amen,</hi> into <hi>So be it,</hi> which is plainly repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnant to his meaning, as alſo to the practice of the whole Church. For they
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:32773:77"/>cannot ſay for their excuſe, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to thoſe, who ſpake in the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> tongue (for <hi>Amen</hi> is <hi>Hebrew</hi>) ſince he wrote to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> who had their publick ſervice in <hi>Greek,</hi> and not in <hi>Hebrew:</hi> A main Argument, that the word <hi>(Amen)</hi> ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in all languages, as it hitherto hath ever been amongſt all Chriſtians, before the dayes of our Reformers; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the moſt learned S. <hi>Aug.</hi> writeth, that it is not lawful to turn <hi>Amen,</hi> into any other vulgar language, without the ſcandal of the whole Church. <hi>Aug. epiſt.</hi> 18. <hi>and</hi> 2. <hi>de D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. cap.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>To conclude, I cannot but much mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veil at the ſimplicity of the common people, who notwithſtanding the great light of their reformed goſpel, ſee not the looſneſs and vanity of this their Leaders cavil. For neither the Maſters, or Schollars, are ſo ſenſeleſs, I hope as to ſay, that their own ſervice conſiſting partly of the Pſalmes of <hi>David</hi> (the hardeſt part of all the Bible) and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of leſſons taken out of the Old and
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:32773:77"/>New Teſtament, is underſtood of all the people preſent thereat; ſince the greateſt Divines that ever were, durſt never ſay ſo much of themſelves. How wrongfully then do they wrangle with us about this matter? But perhaps they will ſay, that though the ſimple people underſtand not the hard places, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Pſalmes and Service, yet (to their great comfort) they underſtand at leaſt ſome part thereof: The ſame ſay we of our Maſs, and of our ſimple people who aſſiſt thereat: and ſo I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude as I began in the Title of this book. <hi>By thine own mouth I judge thee, naughty ſervant.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:32773:78"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32773:78"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE CONTROVERSIES.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> OF the Rule of Faith. <hi>pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Of the judge of Controverſies in matters of Faith. <hi>pag. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Of the Scriptures difficulty. <hi>pag. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Of Traditions. <hi>pag. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Of the private ſpirit. <hi>pag. 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> If S. <hi>Peters</hi> Faith hath failed. <hi>pag. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> If the Church can erre. <hi>pag. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Of the Churches inviſibility. <hi>pag. 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Of her <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality. <hi>pag. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Of her <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity. <hi>pag. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Of S. <hi>Peters</hi> Headſhip. <hi>pag. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Of a ſecular Princes Headſhip. <hi>pag. 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Of Antichriſt. <hi>pag. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Whether none but God, can forgive ſins. <hi>pag. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:32773:79"/>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Whether we ought to confeſs to none but of God. <hi>pag. 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> Of Pardons. <hi>pag. 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> Whether the actions and paſſions of the Saints, are profitable to us. <hi>pag. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> Of works of Supererogation. <hi>pag. 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19.</hi> Of Free will. <hi>pag. 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20.</hi> Of keeping the Commandments. <hi>pag. 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21.</hi> Of Faith and good works. <hi>pag. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22.</hi> Whether good works are merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. <hi>pag. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23.</hi> Whether Faith once had, cannot be loſt. <hi>pag. 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24.</hi> Of Gods inevitable decree who ſhall be damned, and who ſaved. <hi>pag. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25.</hi> Whether we ought to aſſure our ſelves of our ſalvation. <hi>pag. 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26.</hi> Whether every one hath his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel-keeper. <hi>pag. 66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>27.</hi> Whether Angels pray not for us. <hi>pag. 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28.</hi> Whether we may not pray to them. <hi>pag. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29.</hi> Whether they can help us, or no. <hi>pag. 71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30.</hi> Of Saints apparitions. <hi>pag. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31.</hi> Whether they know what paſſeth in earth. <hi>pag. 74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32.</hi> Whether they pray not for us. <hi>pag. 70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:32773:79"/>
                  <hi>33.</hi> Whether we may alleadge their merits, in favour of our ſelves. <hi>pag. 79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>34.</hi> Whether we may not pray unto them. <hi>pag. 82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>35.</hi> Of the Relicks of Saints. <hi>pag. 85</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>36.</hi> Of hallowing of Creatures. <hi>pag. 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>37.</hi> Of the neceſſity of Baptiſm. <hi>pag. 89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>38.</hi> Of Confirmation. <hi>pag. 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>39.</hi> Of the laſt ſupper. <hi>pag. 92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>40.</hi> Of receiving under one kind. <hi>pag. 96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>41.</hi> Of the ſacrifice of the Maſs. <hi>pag. 98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>42.</hi> Of extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction. <hi>pag. 101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>43.</hi> Of holy Orders. <hi>pag. 103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>44.</hi> Of Religious vows. <hi>pag. 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>45.</hi> Of faſting, and abſtinence from meats. <hi>pag. 108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>46.</hi> Of <hi>Limbus Patrum. pag. 110</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>47.</hi> Of Purgatory. <hi>pag. 115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>48.</hi> Of making of Images. <hi>pag. 119</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>49.</hi> Of worſhipping Images. <hi>pag. 123</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>50.</hi> Of making of the picture of God. <hi>pag. 131</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>51.</hi> Of bleſſing with the ſigne of the Croſs. <hi>pag. 134</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>52.</hi> Of ſervice in an unknown tongue. <hi>pag. 135</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
